- You cannot control what
a great military event
can set loose. More battle
casualties than US forces had
suffered in every war combined
down to that point happened in two
days. Two and a half months after
that, George B. McClellan's army
engaged with Lee's army in what came to be
called the Seven Days Battles at Richmond,
36,000 casualties. So
those two together just
showed that this was gonna
be on a totally different
scale. He added a
psychological twist. What,
what Grant envisioned his doing, and
Sheridan actually did it in the Shenandoah
Valley before Sherman did it
in Georgia, is go into an
agriculturally productive area,
burn the mills, kill the livestock,
destroy the crops, lay waste to it so that
it can't be a logistical support of the
Confederacy anymore. Sheridan did it in
the Shenandoah Valley, and then Sherman
did it in Georgia. But Sherman said,
"But I'm also going to break them
psychologically. I'm gonna show them that
my army can go wherever it wants to go
whenever it wants to go, and there's nothing
Jefferson Davis can do about it." The great
forces are all that matters and individuals
don't really matter notion of history I
think is ridiculous. Individuals
really matter. For the
United States, Lincoln and Grant
matter beyond calculation-
... in this war. And on the Confederate side,
if you take Lee out of the picture, the
war doesn't last nearly as long as it
does. In terms of causation, if you take
slavery out of the picture,
there is no Civil War, period.
- The following is a conversation
with Gary Gallagher, a
historian of the American Civil War.
This is the Lex Fridman Podcast. To
support it, please check out our sponsors
in the description where you can
also find links to contact me,
ask questions, give feedback,
and so on. And now, dear
friends, here's Gary Gallagher. The
American Civil War broke out in 1861.
What were the causes of the
Civil War? Could it have been
avoided, or was it inevitable?
- I don't know if anything is inevitable in
history, but it's certainly safe to say
that the conditions were in
place to make it possible-
... by the winter of 1860, '61, and
the conditions that made it possible
were all related to the
institution of slavery and
its effects both in the states where
slavery was allowed and the states
where it was not allowed. And there
had been a series of tensions
that grew in the decade
preceding the 1850s.
It's not that one side wants to get
rid of slavery and the other side
wants to protect slavery. I'm talking about
the white people in the United States now
who would be making the
political decisions.
It's a question of whether slavery was
going to be able to expand into federal
territories. That is what really created
the starkest difference between
the two sections in the
1850s, even in the late 1840s.
The issues that came to most, uh,
perilous a point in the view of many people
then had to do with whether slavery would
be allowed only where it already
existed, or would it be allowed to
expand. If it could expand,
then it seemed that it might
be conceivable at some point even
that the slaveholding states
could end up with a majority.
They were in a minority by 1860,
'61 and feeling beleaguered, feeling
threatened. They'd long since lost
the population race to the free states.
Early in the nation, the most powerful states
were slaveholding states. Virginia was by
far the most important state.
Four of the first five
presidents were from Virginia,
all slaveholders, all prominent
members of the slaveholding class. Those
days were long gone by the late 1850s.
- So that's an important thing to
say. It wasn't before the Civil
War a discussion about abolishing
slavery. It's about whether
slavery, the institution of
slavery should be expanded.
- Allowed to expand into federal
territories. There, there is a portion
of the white population that
is adamantly in favor of
getting rid of slavery immediately. The abolitionists,
they... There was even a political party
called the Liberty Party, that ran a
candidate in 1840 and they got a handful of
thousand votes. They reached their
high point in 1844. They got about
two and a half percent of the vote.
The abolitionists are a tiny minority
among the— even in the North, tiny
minority among the white people
of the United States. The African
American population, nearly four
million of them by 1860, of
course, would have embraced it
instantly and yearned for it. But in
the white population, the abolitionists are
a tiny minority. They are much despised
even across much of the North
because they were seen as agitators
who roiled the Union and
deepened rifts that might
bring a significant political break.
- So how did this escalate
to a civil war, this
almost policy discussion about the
institution of slavery? How did it
actually escalate?
- It escalated into a civil war because
in the presidential election of
1860... There'd been two party systems
in the United States. The first
party system, the Republicans, the Jeffersonian
Republicans versus the Federalists.
After that, there was, the two parties
were the Whig Party against the
Democratic Party. The Democratic Party grew
out of the Jeffersonian Republican Party.
It's the same party.
The Whig Party foundered to a significant
degree on the issue of slavery.
How do you maintain a national party
that has a wing in the Southern
states and has a wing
in the Northern free states that
can handle the issue of slavery?
The Democrats managed to do that. The
Whigs could not do it, and so the Whig
Party ran their last candidate
in 1852, presidential candidate,
significant candidate. And the
Republican Party emerged in the
mid-1850s, took most of the
old Whigs into the Republican
ranks and one of the Republican,
the key Republican platform plank
was no expansion of slavery
into the territories.
Not abolish slavery, no
expansion. That was the key in
1856 when they ran their first
candidate. In 1860, that
is again the key plank in the Republican
platform. The Republican platform in
1860 says where slavery exists it will
continue, but it cannot expand into the
territories. When white Southerners
saw that, that meant that
they were doomed to become an increasingly
minority section in the nation,
and you would have a federal
government increasingly dominated by the
free states that could then do the one
thing that the white South could
not countenance, and that is
tamper with the institution
of slavery in the South.
The presidential election of 1860
brought the destruction of the
last national party, which was
the Democrats. They couldn't even
settle on a candidate, so you end up with
a Northern Democratic candidate running,
Stephen A. Douglas, and a
Southern candidate running. The
convention fractured and John C.
Breckinridge ran on the, on the Southern
Democrat platform. You had a
Unionist candidate running who just
didn't wanna talk about slavery, let's
talk about the Union, and you had Lincoln
running as a Republican. When Lincoln
won, the white South looked at Lincoln
winning. Here's a guy who
has said that he doesn't
think slavery would expand, but
he'd said more than that. He
scared the white South more because
in 1858, both Lincoln and William
Henry Seward, these are two
prominent, prominent Republicans,
had said basically in separate
speeches, the House Divided Speech
on Lincoln's part, the Irrepressible
Conflict Speech on Seward's part,
that the nation could not continue in
the long term half slave and half free.
And everybody in the South knew
which way they wanted it to be. They
would want it to be no slavery.
And so Lincoln's election
scared the white South enough
so that seven of the 15
slave-holding states seceded in
response to Lincoln's election.
They seceded between December 20th,
when South Carolina went out,
and the end of February. You
had the deep South went out.
- What was the general view amongst
the populace towards slavery? Let's
kind of lay it out. Let's you know,
for the audience looking back,
let's put ourselves in the
mind space of how people
saw the world, how people saw slavery,
how people saw African Americans.
- Well, the baseline among the
white Americans, there were about
31, shade more than 31 million Americans
in 1860 for the census of 1860.
About four million of them
were African Americans,
three and a half million of those
enslaved in the South. Anyway,
among the white population,
the average attitude toward Black
people is what we would call
profoundly prejudiced. Doesn't matter whether
you... A lot of people think this is a
Southern white thing. They're the only ones
who were prejudiced. By our standards, the
overwhelming majority of
people in the free states
were also deeply prejudiced.
It's important to
keep in mind that attitudes towards
slavery and attitudes toward race
do not, they're not necessarily the
same. I mean, you could be against
slavery and still be prejudiced against
Black people. By our standards, many
abolitionists were prejudiced
against Black people. They...
But the overwhelming
majority of the white North,
in the North, often had a hard time getting
my students to understand the demographics
in 1860. The free states in
1860 were more than 98% white.
98% white. African Americans are a tiny
minority in the free states. Black
people lived in the 15 slaveholding
states in 1860. Most of
the white North, by our
standards, was very prejudiced.
They were against the expansion of
slavery into the territories because
they thought that would circumscribe
white opportunities to make an economic
life in these federal territories,
and they didn't want that to happen.
About 45% of the people who lived
in the free states were Democrats.
Most Democrats had no problem with
slavery. I mean, absolutely no
problem with the institution of
slavery. There would be more
problems among Republicans,
especially with extension of slavery,
although many Democrats, white
Democrats in the North
were against that as well.
The white South was overwhelmingly
in favor of slavery. You
often read the argument, the kind
of neo-Confederate argument that
they'll talk about how most Confederate
soldiers didn't own slaves. That's true.
The a large majority of families in
the South did not own a single slave.
But all white Southerners had a stake
in slavery. They had a stake in
it as a form of labor control,
but more important than that, they had
a stake in it as a means of social
control. They knew, no matter what
they said later in the Jim Crow era of
how happy Black people were in the institution
of slavery, they knew that Black people,
of course, did not want to be enslaved, and
they were afraid of what would happen if
they weren't enslaved anymore. They had in
the backs of their minds Haiti. Is that
what's gonna... If you live in one of the
coastal districts of South Carolina where
90% of the residents are enslaved
and you're a white person, you
probably don't sleep all that soundly
at night if you think there's any
chance that the Black people are not
gonna remain under the control of the
white people. So all white people in
the South had a stake in slavery,
not just some. All of them did, and
there were all kinds of ways that
it would go back and forth.
If you were a modest
farmer and grew a little bit of cotton, you
didn't have your own cotton gin, you...
but your more wealthy neighbor had a
gin, could gin your cotton there, and
then you would take your turn on the slave
patrol, the slave patrols. So there's a
reciprocity in that regard.
- This is perhaps a bit outside the
scope of what we'll talk about today,
but just to lay out the context
on slavery in general in human
history, we should say that slavery was
ubiquitous. It existed
in virtually every major
civilization in the history of humans.
Mesopotamia, Egypt, Greece,
Rome, China, the Islamic
world, Africa, the Americas,
North and South America.
We should also say something
that, as I was looking into this,
another big topic, which is the Atlantic
slave trade. And it was surprising to me,
the stat I wasn't aware of, I would venture
to say most Americans probably don't know,
that only 4% of African slaves were brought
to North America, to the United States.
- Brazil is the main destination.
- Brazil, the Caribbean was
over 90%, 4.9 million in
Brazil, 4 million in the Caribbean,
and it was also the last of the
Americas to abolish the slave trade. So
only 4% of the Atlantic slave trade
went to the United States. So there's--
the story of human slavery
is one that reaches deep
into our history and
geographically is much
larger than we often study in the
context of the United States.
- One thing the war, the Civil War, which
I'll just call the war for the rest of
our discussion, I mean, one
thing it did was end slavery
in four years in the United States.
Whereas in the absence of that war, it
might have gone on for decades. I think the
United States would have had the
ignominious distinction of being the last
place to get rid of slavery, would have been
after Brazil, would have been after Spanish
Cuba, because it was thriving in
the United States in 1860. It was
making the transition from
cash crop agriculture-
... to other, to industrial
applications and other applications
growing of non-- not growing, growing
just cotton and rice and sugar. It was--
There was a time in the literature
when people argued that the war
was needless, the Civil War was needless because
slavery was on its way out. That's absolutely
wrong. It was not on its way out. It was
thriving. Lincoln said at one point he
thought it might have lasted another
fifty years, and I don't know how many
years it would have lasted, but I think it would
have lasted longer than it did in either Cuba or
Brazil if it hadn't, if the
war hadn't taken place.
- So slavery was flourishing
in the United States from-
- Flourishing.
- ... from an economics
perspective- ... especially.
- The wealthiest part...
The 1860 census is our
friend, and it tells us that
the people who controlled the
most wealth in the United States were
slaveholders, and their property in
slaves alone, not their other
holdings, not their land holdings,
just property in slaves were valued at
about three billion dollars. The value
of all industries, all railroads,
all of that put together,
fewer than two point five billion dollars.
So the people who controlled the most
wealth, by far, were
the slaveholding class.
- So it was the most valuable
industry in the United States,
and perhaps it is the reason,
Again, a bit out of scope, but
maybe it helps lay out the land.
Let's look at the nineteenth century. So
most slave-owning societies of the
era were able to abolish slavery
without people dying at the mass
scale that we'll discuss. So
Britain freed eight hundred
thousand slaves in 1833-
... By buying their freedom. Russia freed
twenty-three million serfs in 1861 with
a decree, so legally. Brazil, which
imported more than ten times as many
enslaved Africans as the United
States, abolished slavery in 1888
through basic ordinary legislation.
No violence. Why did
the US have a civil war
with an estimated seven hundred
and fifty thousand people dead in
order to abolish slavery?
- Yes. That's-- Let's talk just for a second
about the seven hundred and fifty thousand
dead soldiers we're talking about.
The number for years was six
hundred and eighteen thousand,
and that's been revised lately.
I think we're probably certainly more than seven
hundred thousand. By far the bloodiest war in,
in our history as a percentage of
the population off the charts,
by far the bloodiest. I think there's
a big difference between Great
Britain doing it and the United States
doing it, is Great Britain did it in other
places. There weren't millions of enslaved
people in Great Britain at the time.
It's-- I think, for them, it might
have been a little bit easier to free
enslaved people who don't live among
you than it... In the United States,
the ante is up for the Confederacy because they,
the enslaved people lived here, and I think they
were, a lot of them were afraid of them
and what would happen if they weren't
enslaved anymore. The war goes
from... It doesn't begin as a
war to end slavery. There's
a major shift in the war,
begins in the summer of
1862, where you add to the
war. The war aim for the United
States initially is to suppress the
rebellion, which is what they
called this. They didn't call
it the Civil War for the most part during
the war. It's the War of the Rebellion.
That's the goal initially. As the
war goes on and becomes costlier
and more all-encompassing, they decide
that they're not gonna be able to suppress
the rebellion unless they also
strike at slavery, because
slavery underpins the
Confederate war-making capacity.
You have enslaved labor that keeps the
economy going and allows the Confederacy
to mobilize between eighty-five and
ninety percent of all their white
military-aged males. It's an
astonishing mobilization. It's only
possible because enslaved labor keeps
the economy going. If you take that
enslaved labor away, it deals a significant
blow to the Confederate economy and,
and by extension, to its ability
to wage a nineteenth century war.
- So the Emancipation Proclamation
was in part a military strategy.
- Abraham Lincoln based it entirely
on his war-making power as
commander-in-chief in a time of open
rebellion. His inclination, there's
no-- He's often been criticized
for not including the soaring
language he was capable of in the
Emancipation Proclamation. One
historian likened it to a bill of
lading. It had all the soaring
language of a bill of lading. He
did that on purpose. He did it because he,
he doesn't have the power to strike at
slavery in the absence of a war. The
president doesn't. And
he did it because he knows that
he can't win the war with only
Republicans in the army. He needs to keep
Democrats on board with the war as well.
They're not in favor of emancipation.
The one way that they might accept it
is as a tool to help achieve union, and
to do that we've got to strike at
the rebels this way, strike at
slavery. That will hurt their war effort, and it
will also punish the people who brought on the war,
and that would make... So
Lincoln hoped that by basing it
strictly on his war power, it
might be more widely accepted
across all parts of the
loyal states and not as
controversial as it was. It was still
intensely controversial. It alienated
many Democrats when he issued it,
who said, "You're changing what this
war is about. We're willing to shed
our blood and maybe risk our lives to
restore the union of the founders.
I'm not gonna risk my life to
free a Black person." That's a very,
very common attitude among Democrats.
- So what did the Emancipation
Proclamation actually do? It
emphasized the freeing
of slaves in the South.
- It's even more complicated than that.
The only place that Lincoln said he had
the power as the war leader to
strike at slavery is where the
rebels were actually still in
rebellion and in control. So
any place where the US Army was in
control, any place-- He said that
it is in essence United States
territory now. I can't free them there
because I don't have the power. I can
only free them where we don't have the
power. So he exempted parts of
states and areas in the South
that it didn't apply to as of the
moment he signed it. Going forward,
any place that the United States Army
went where it hadn't been on January 1st,
1863, the Emancipation Proclamation
applied and enslaved people would be
freed by it. At the, literally at the
time he signed it, he didn't free
anybody because he's only saying, "I can free
them where we're not in control. We have to be
in control for this to have effect
and for this to have power."
- So in part, this is why the army was the
boundary which the freeing was happening.
- It's, it's, it's absolutely the boundary,
and Congress had already passed what was
called the Second Confiscation Act.
It passed this in July of 1862
that announced that all
enslaved people belonging
to rebels were free. It didn't apply
to people who could prove they were
unionists living in the South and owned
slaves. Lincoln didn't make that distinction
in the Emancipation Proclamation.
His proclamation is broader than
the Second Confiscation Act was.
- Okay. There's so many tangents we can
take, but let's zoom out once again.
There's a difference between cause, as
you've talked about, cause and motivation.
- Absolutely.
- Quite a large number of
people volunteered to fight.
- In fact, a majority of all the
soldiers who fought on both
sides were volunteers during
the Civil War. About 3 million
served, 2.2 million in the United
States, 800, 900,000 in the Confederacy.
It's, again, I talk about things that are hard to
get students to understand. This is one of them.
They have to separate... The
causation and motivation are
often conflated, and not just by students
but also by lots of talking heads on
newscasts in the United States who
don't know anything about United States
history- ... but know what they
know. In terms of causation, if
you take slavery out of the picture,
there is no Civil War, period.
That's not a long conversation you need.
You ask the question. That's the answer.
Let's go to the next question.
The next question is, okay,
so were most white people
motivated to put on blue uniforms
because they wanted to kill
slavery? The answer to that is no,
they were not. They were motivated
to put on blue uniforms
to salvage the Union,
which they saw as a unique gift that the
founding generation, based on the
bloodshed in the American Revolution,
had bequeathed the successive generations.
And the two key parts of what the
Union meant for them was, number one,
you had a voice in your own government,
and someone will always say now to me,
"Well, but women couldn't
vote." That's right.
The people who could vote by our
standards were limited in the 19th
century, but within the context
of the Western world in
1860, the United States had by
far the broadest franchise, by
far. And so they argued that's one
thing the Union gives us, and it
also gives us the chance to rise
economically. Doesn't guarantee that you can
succeed, but it means you're not
doomed to be what your father was.
And those are worth fighting for. And
so I will put on a uniform so the
slave-holding aristocrats and
oligarchs, which is what they called
them, of the South, they said they're not...
They don't really believe in democracy.
It's an oligarchy- ... in the South.
It's a slavery-based oligarchy,
and we know which way Europe's going,
they said. The revolutions of the
1840s failed in Europe. Europe's going
the wrong way. They're going toward
more aristocracy, more oligarchy, more...
And we are the last hope.
When Lincoln spoke of
the last best hope of Earth,
which he did in one of his most
memorable phrases, he's meaning
that the United States is a
beacon of small D democracy in a
Western world that seems to be turning
the other way. And those soldiers,
it meant, it meant it was that important
to them. They are citizens in a republic
that people shed blood to
establish, and we can't let it
go. Part of the compact is
I'm a citizen. I derive these
benefits from this
republic, from the Union.
I can have a voice in government. I can
rise economically or have the chance to.
I owe my service to that republic.
That's what most of them would've
said if you'd pressed them on why they're doing it.
Doesn't mean everybody was on fire with ideology
that way. Some guys would say, "Well, you
know what? I'm broke, and I'm gonna get
fed and clothed in the army." But this
sense of exceptionalism, exceptionalism's
unpopular now in the United
States, but Americans had a
sense of themselves as a truly
exceptionalist society within the
context of the Western world.
- And as a small aside terminology-wise,
blue is the Union or what we
think of as the United States,
and red is the Confederacy.
- Yes. On the maps, the Confederate
units are red blocks. And the United
States units are blue
blocks. That's right.
- And, uh
- That is correct.
- And the North and the South is another
way we'll refer to it just to clarify.
- And let me have a very brief
rant on North and South.
I prefer to see this as a war between
two mid-19th-century republics,
One of which didn't last very long
and spent its whole life in the midst
of a great war. There were 15
slaveholding states in 1860.
Only 11 of them seceded
from the United States.
- Even though there's 13 stars.
We'll talk about that.
- We'll talk about that demented notion
of things in just a minute, but only 11
leave. So there are four slaveholding
states in the United States: Kentucky, and
Missouri, and Maryland, and Delaware
remain in the United States. So
it's not just North versus South.
Those states are all part of the
South. It's the United States
versus the Confederacy.
- But see how you referred to it
as the United States. So the
Union is also referred
to as the United States
- That's correct. Yes, yes
- But the Confederacy was, as
you write about, a set of
people who also had a sense
of nationalism, pride
- Well, and took their founding document.
I mean, it took the whole summer of
1787 in Philadelphia, that
hot, steamy, humid summer of
1787 to come up with the
Constitution. The Confederates did it
quickly 'cause they basically had the
US Constitution here, a blank piece of
paper over here
... copied most of the Constitution over
here, just changed the parts that they needed
to make sure slavery was protected,
and you didn't have the wrong
kind of tariffs and so forth. That's one
reason they could do it so quickly. It's
absolutely based on
the government they've been thriving under,
which is under the United States Constitution.
Both sides claimed they were the true
inheritors of the revolutionary generation.
That was one of their... They
all... Jefferson Davis loved the
Declaration of Independence. The
Declaration is Abraham Lincoln's favorite
document. They just liked
different parts of it
- So we should think of
this as two republics
- I argue that. That makes
many people very angry
- I will make many people angry today
- They say that I am conferring
legitimacy on the Confederacy that they
don't deserve,
and my response to that is they have
a national government. They have a
Senate. They have a Congress. They have
an army. They have a navy. They have
departments. They... It's...
It walks like a duck. It
quacks like a duck. In the end, it's a
slaughtered duck faster than it would've been
because the United States
military forces crushed it
- We should say that you are respected,
admired, loved by most people on both sides
in, from a perspective sense. You're
deeply respected by historians of
Civil War and just historians of
American history. But of
course, when you do your job
well on a controversial topic in a
controversial period of human history-
... you're going to get, hopefully
an equal amount of critics on both
sides. And that's when you do your
job well. So sometimes when we
speak today, some of the
controversial, quote-unquote,
controversial things that you express
are controversial from that small
minority of folks on both
sides for different reasons
- Yes. I won't be... One of my favorite
pieces of hate mail I got was an
email where this guy, I had... He
was upset that I referred to the
Confederacy as a slave-holding republic
that was... And he said that he
hoped I would develop virulent pancreatic
cancer and die a horrible death. Not
just regular pancreatic cancer. He
wanted virulent pancreatic cancer
And then he signed his name and said he'd
be happy to talk to me anytime I wanted
to
- Yeah. I'm sure that would
be a wonderful conversation
But there's also really
strong senses throughout,
throughout the United States,
the United States, of the,
this diversity of opinion of
what is the United States
- Of course. Yes
- And that's where the
passion is really rooted
- Both sides claim... In
the election of 1860,
Douglas talked about how much he loved the
Union. Lincoln talked about how much he
loved the Union. Breckinridge talked
about how much he loved the Union.
They're all... And John Bell, who's the
Unionist, the Constitutional Union-
That's all he talked about. They just had
different versions of what the Union was
- And that's why I love this country. I think
it's the greatest country on Earth, and it
has a bunch of people that very
strongly disagree with each other.
Of course, hopefully never again
escalating to the degree that it
did during this period of time.
So we talked about the blue people on
the map and the red people on the map.
It may be a silly thing to ask,
but sticking with the motivation,
why would, let's say, a farm boy in
Ohio- ... want to die for the Union?
- That is the most important, and I didn't
even ask you to ask that question. That's
the, that's the hardest thing-
- Let's be honest. You paid me a lot
of money to ask that question, yeah.
- I didn't think it was so much.
- Okay. I'm sorry. Go
ahead. I won't distract.
- No. The, I tell my students at the beginning
of my Civil War class that if they couldn't
explain, I didn't use Ohio. I said, "If you
can't explain why a farmer from Vermont-
... would put on a blue uniform and
pick up a musket to make South Carolina
come back in, why didn't he just say, 'Great.
South Carolina's gone. I never liked them
anyway. This is a better union.'
If you can't explain that,
then you can't understand the Civil War." And
the key to that, I'll come back to it, is
union because he would've said,
"If we allow South Carolina to go
That means that other places
could go and you could dismantle.
And the only reason they're going is because
they didn't like who was elected president.
They didn't say that Lincoln was corrupt. They
didn't say Republicans bought the election.
They just didn't like who won the
election. And so if the republic is
so fragile that it can't have
an election without having the
people who didn't like who won
leave, then the founders had wasted
their time, the revolution was for
nothing, all that bloodshed meant
nothing. You had to step up and save this
precious republic that had put in place
by the revolutionary generation
and gave its citizens the benefits
that I've already talked about. That's why
they would put on a uniform and risk their
life, because they believed a
citizen... These are citizen soldiers.
We don't know what that means so much now.
because we have a professional
military establishment now. Not--
I mean, even when I was younger, there was
still a draft, and but that's gone now.
And so we don't understand what the
concept of citizen soldier was, that you
owe something back to the republic
that has conveyed these things
to you, and that's why the guy from
Vermont or New Hampshire or Ohio
would put on a uniform and
go into military service.
- Is it possible for us to understand
that level of love of nation
and believe in nation? Is this, is this
very distant from what America is today?
- I actually think many people probably still
feel that way, but they're not the ones
who are on television-
... most of the time. Republicans
in the midst of the war commented
about the fact that even with
this gigantic conflict going
on, immigration continued
at a high level. People
coming into a nation that
was in the middle of a great
war. And they said, "This is
a testament to the promise
of the United States."
And I think that promise
continues. I mean, we've argued about...
As with so many things, Americans have
no sense of history. They believe we've
never argued about immigration before.
We've always argued about immigration, with
some people always saying, "Shut the door.
They're ruining us. The Italians are ruining
us. The Irish are Catholics. They're ruining
us. God, the Southern Europeans are
even worse than, than the Irish were."
It's-- The people change, the
arguments stay very much the
same, and I think it's really telling
that in the midst of the war, people
would say, "Look at our republic.
It is-- It offers so much to people
that even in the midst of this
great war, they're still coming-
... to the United States."
- And like you said, both
sides, both these republics
claimed, for example, George Washington.
- Yes. They both claim... I'll leave it at
that. They both claim George Washington.
They wanted to be right
with the man, which is what George
Washington was. He's the indispensable
man, no question. Both sides
wanted him on their side. They
both quoted Thomas Jefferson,
although Confederates were a
little more leery of Jefferson
'cause he's too complicated for them
sometimes. But no, they wanted to be
right with the founders and claimed to
be right with the founders. The Confederates
would say, "The Constitution allowed
slavery. What are you talking about we're out
of step with the Constitution? We're in step
with the Con- You're the ones who are
out of step with the Constitution."
- What about the topic of states'
rights? At the very least-
- I love state rights. State rights...
I mean, I love the way people use
it with the Civil War. They associate
it solely with Southern states-
... of course. State rights is always
available in United States history for
somebody who's not happy with what
the federal government is doing.
During the War of 1812, it was New
England that most often talked-
... about resorting to state rights. They had
a convention where they sort of wandered over
towards secession territory
in the Hartford Convention.
We think of it as state rights
because as you lead up to the Civil
War, you hear con- white Southerners
talking about it all the
time. "We need our state
rights." I always love to ask
people who say that, "What are all the state
rights? Give me-- List the state rights that
the white South is concerned."
You know, "Give me the top three. No, really,
just give me the top two." There's only one.
The state right that they're worried
about is the right of their state to
interpose its power between a federal
government that might try to interfere with
slavery and a state government that wants
to maintain it. That's the state right that
matters then. Northern states also
resorted to state rights during this, the
ramp-up to the Civil War, with what
were called personal liberty laws. They
tried to interpose their state power in
between a federal government that would
use its power to to force escaped,
enslaved people back into slavery.
It's whoever's unhappy with the federal
government, the concept of state rights is
available, and both sides used it.
- And of course, the beautiful, dark,
ironic hypocrisy was illustrated by the
Confederacy when they were the first to
pass a national draft in American history.
- Like, irony is wonderful- ... in history.
Another thing that I love to teach
is that the most intrusive
central government in American
history, by far, until deep
into the 20th century, was the
Confederate central government, because
it had to do things to keep the war
going that it couldn't have done unless
the central government stepped in,
such as passing the first national
conscription law in American history. The
government, the US government never forced
people into uniform before the Civil War.
The Confederates did it first. They did
it in the spring of 1862. They passed a
national graduated income tax.
And when taxing didn't work,
when their money became so devalued, they
then passed what they called the tax in
kind. They would take a percentage of
your crop. They allowed the government to
impress horses and mules
and enslaved labor to work
on All of these were intrusions
from the central government that
drove true state rights people
crazy in the Confederacy.
Confederates didn't have political parties
because they said the founders didn't want them,
so we won't have them. But what
they did have was a sort of
nationalist, "We're gonna let the central government
do whatever it needs to do." That's Jefferson
Davis' wing, and Robert E. Lee's over
there, too. And the people like the
vice president, Alexander Stephens,
who said, "You can't do all this stuff
because the states
should have more power."
The only reason the war lasted as long as it did
is because the central government did things
no one ever would have believed they
would do. He also got rid of habeas
corpus just like Abraham Lincoln
did in selected situations.
- And of course, we should really emphasize
that on both sides, those volunteers,
the on the Confederacy, there's
a very large number of people
percentage-wise that volunteered
to fight. And then I
believe the volunteer
period was one year, and
then there's all kind of funky stuff that
the that the government started doing to
trap those people into then serving and-
- Here's what the Confederacy did.
They... Nobody thinks the
war's gonna last a long time-
... in the spring of 1861.
So if you enlist for a year-
... that's probably plenty of time to
finish this war. Well, a year goes by and a
significant percentage of the Confederate
men under arms are due to get out. So what
the Confederate Congress
did was pass conscription.
We're gonna put every- make everybody
liable to three-year service.
And in the midst of doing that,
all you guys who volunteered for
one year are now in for two more years.
Well, that outraged... I mean, "That's,
you're breaking faith with us," they said.
They didn't stop there.
Later they revised it when the war kept
going on and then the three years guys were
gonna get out, then the Congress stepped in and
said, "You're in for the duration." The bottom
line is, the Confederacy ever
gets you in uniform, you don't
get out because they keep changing
the rules on you. And that
was considered, national conscription
was considered a fundamental
abridgment of individual rights by many people.
That's something the government should never
force a citizen into uniform. A citizen
should volunteer their service.
The US government waited a year, then
it did it in the spring of 1863,
although it always respected
original terms of enlistment.
Never made it the war for the
duration the way the Confederacy did.
- Quick pause for a bathroom
break if it's okay.
Quick 10-second shout-out to our sponsors.
Check them out in the description.
It really is the best way to
support this podcast. Go to
lexfridman.com/sponsors.
And now, dear friends,
back to my conversation
with Gary Gallagher.
All right, we're back. There's so many
different directions we can go, but
I am somebody who believes that individuals
can steer the direction of history.
So one angle to look at here is,
some of the legendary historical
figures from this time.
Let's talk about some of the key figures
of the Civil War. We have Abraham Lincoln,
of course, the President of the United States
who held the Union together and turned the war
into a fight for a new birth of
freedom. Jefferson Davis, who you
mentioned, President of the
Confederacy. Ulysses S.
Grant, somebody we'll talk
about quite a bit, General in
Chief of the Union
armies. Robert E. Lee on
the other side, the commander of
the Army of Northern Virginia,
somebody who you have studied for
decades now. We'll talk a lot
about him. There's Sherman, there's Stonewall
Jackson, there's Frederick Douglass,
there is McClellan, there is John
Brown, a militant abolitionist.
Many more figures, but let's look at three
at first. Let's look at Lincoln,
Grant, and Lee. Lincoln first. So
Abraham Lincoln, we have
this backwoods lawyer with a
single year of schooling
who somehow outgrew every
polished man around him and became one
of the most consequential leaders in
human history. So what do we
need to understand? What can we
possibly understand at
a 10,000-foot level,
About Lincoln that made it
all possible? What was it
about Lincoln's mind that
made this man do what he did?
- Almost nobody continues to go up in
my estimation as I get older and
older, but Lincoln is one of the people
who does. And Lincoln is quite frankly
a mystery to me. I don't see how you
get Abraham Lincoln out of someone who
came from his very poor background. You
said he had a year of schooling. You're being very
generous to him there. He didn't even really have a
year of formal schooling.
And you end up with a person
who is the most eloquent president
we've ever had by a very wide margin
and I think even more
eloquent than Jefferson,
and who is able to distill
into the fewest possible
words the most complex ideas and
topics imaginable and just have them
ring in a way that almost no one
is able to do. He is someone...
He had an ego, but I think one of
his real gifts was the ability to
put his ego aside and keep his eye on
the goal. He was able to really focus,
and he focused relentlessly
on, number one,
suppressing the rebellion
and restoring the Union,
but also getting... He hated the
institution of slavery. He's not an
abolitionist, but he hated the institution
of slavery and he was very happy to
see that slavery was added to
the roster of what the United
States would insist on
at the end of the war.
He's able to let all the other
things go. He can pay attention to
many things, but he never loses his...
his principal focus was, "How do I
maintain this great war?"
And it's an all en- it's
really hard to get people
to understand the scope
of the Civil War. There are 31
million people in the United States
then. About a shade more than 3
million put on uniforms. It would
be as if we had 35 to 40 million
people under arms now. For the Confederates,
it would be like having more like
55 million people- ... under arms
as a percentage of the population.
The dead would be between 6
million and 7.5 million, depending
on how you count it. The scope
is just... During the Gulf Wars,
The New York Times put a picture of every
United States service person who was
killed, put a picture in the paper
over the scope of those wars,
and that is about as many people
as were shot in a few hours at
Antietam. It's just very different to
get students now to understand the
different scale, and that's what
Lincoln's dealing with. How
do I keep the focus on a war
that is becoming far more
costly than anyone imagined,
and eating up our young manpower at a
rate that no one... There's never been
anything in our history to prepare
the United States for this. The
Winfield Scott captured Mexico City
with an army of fewer than 15,000
during the war with Mexico.
U.S. Grant has 120,000. I mean, the whole
scale is just so different that it's
hard to come to terms with it.
And that's what Lincoln was
dealing with. I think the fact
that he was willing to surround
himself with really able
counselors is important. Who does
he put in his cabinet? He puts his
main rivals in the cabinet. He
put William Henry Seward in his
cabinet, who's the most famous Republican
in the country. He puts Salmon P. Chase,
who's a very smart and effective and
ambitious person from Ohio, in his
cabinet. He surrounds himself with
people who are capable and energetic
and have their own ambitions, he's not afraid
to do that, all of whom had far better
educations than he had and didn't have
a rural backwoods accent like he did.
It's also a measure of how confident he was. He
didn't pretend to talk a way he, uh, to talk
in a fashion that he- ...
didn't actually talk.
He would've pronounced words in ways that
anybody who went to Harvard would just
sneer at. He didn't, and he knew
they sneered, and he didn't care.
Because eventually, all of them,
except the ones with only a 20-watt
bulb, figured out that
Lincoln was actually probably
smarter than they were and had a better
grasp of things than they did and
brought them around. He really brought
Seward around, which is very impressive.
- Yeah, there's so many fascinating
things about Lincoln. So backwoods of
Kentucky, and Kentucky is a very
important state in this story. And
the right words, the right speeches,
the right debates at this moment in
history. It really does make me wonder,
you know, if Lincoln didn't exist, if
certain humans in history didn't exist,
that everything could have
turned out very differently.
- The great forces are all that matters and
individuals don't really matter notion of
history I think is ridiculous.
Individuals really matter.
For the United States, Lincoln and
Grant matter beyond calculation--
... in this, in this war. And on the Confederate
side, if you take Lee out of the picture, the
war doesn't last nearly as long as
it does. In fact, we'll talk about
this later probably, I think it could
have ended early in the summer of 1862
with slavery still intact.
I mean, in a perverse way,
Lee furthers the cause of
emancipation because he--
extends the war long enough that the
United States says, "We have to do this.
We've gotta get rid of slavery
to defeat the rebels."
- So, and also on the psychological
side, Lincoln is a,
this is a fascinating study because he,
he carried deep depression all his life.
- He had black, black moods
in his life, yes, he did.
- And so for somebody that has to go
through an all-encompassing war,
to be able to sort of survive
through that, to think through that,
without an education,
without any acquired skill
that enables him to be a
commander-in-chief during a time of war.
He's got nothing in the
toolbox, and yet he steps up.
- If you looked at his resume
and Jefferson Davis's--
... in 1860 and said, "Okay, here are the
two guys who are gonna be your respective
commanders-in-chief. Who
do you want on your team?"
Lincoln had no administrative
experience beyond running a little
law office. He had one
two-year term in the House of
Representatives in terms of
national government. He had no
military service to speak of, a
little while in the Black Hawk
War as a junior officer
in the Black Hawk War.
Didn't check any of the education boxes, as
you said. Jefferson Davis was a graduate of
West Point. He'd commanded more
men in the war with Mexico than
most of the men who commanded armies
during the Civil War. He'd chaired the
Senate Committee on Military
Affairs. He'd been Secretary of
War, a lot of administrative experience. He
checked every box. Lincoln checked none of the
boxes, and yet you got Lincoln as a
commander-in-chief. It's really quite
remarkable. He could listen to people
that he thought knew more about
something than he did. That's a
quality that all of our presidents,
to put it mildly, have not
had. Lincoln did have that. He could
listen. He could admit when he was wrong
and change his mind about
things, and he could put up
with obnoxious behavior on
the part of people that
he thought might deliver the goods.
And a perfect example of this
is George Brinton McClellan, whom we'll
talk about later, his young... who was
general-in-chief for a while,
commanded the Army of the Potomac.
In 1861, Lincoln and his
Secretary of State, William Henry
Seward, went to McClellan's house to
talk to McClellan. Went to McClellan's
house. The commander-in-chief goes to
McClellan's house. McClellan wasn't there.
The butler or somebody put them in a
side room. McClellan came home, was
told Lincoln was there.
He went upstairs and then
told the person who worked for him to go tell
the president that he'd be happy to talk to
him some other time. And so
Lincoln just left. He never went
back to see McClellan again,
didn't pitch a fit, filed
that away. Okay, McClellan's an ass, but
I think he might win the war. I mean, he
had that ability to do that,
to put aside that kind of
behavior on the part of someone
if he thought they would deliver.
He just has a number of qualities,
I think, that are very unusual to
find in someone. And as you say, he
did have depressive moments, and
he-- we talk about how, what
bad days presidents have. Now,
Lincoln would have said, I'll take
that president's worst day every
day rather than the days that I get,
for the most part. I mean, he--
it's hard to imagine the
burdens that he carried.
- And at the right time was
just a handful of words
expressed something that no
military could possibly do.
- Explain what the war was about,
why it was worth fighting, what it
meant, his second inaugural address.
I mean, people went-- when people went
to hear the president give his second
inaugural address on that cold day in
1865, what they wanted to hear,
they finally beat the rebel
scum from their point of view. Let's have some
retribution here. What are we going to do to them?
How are we going to make these
people who brought this great war
pay for this? And what does
Lincoln tell them? He tells them
slavery caused it. Everybody knows that
somehow that's the truth, and we're
all implicated in it. I mean, he
didn't tell them anything that
they wanted to hear that
day. And it was-- and it
took great courage, I think, to do
that at that moment, to tell an
audience what they didn't want to hear.
And he did it in the most eloquent
language that any president's-- that's the
greatest speech in American history, the second
inaugural, in my view.
- With malice toward none, with
charity for all, with firmness
in the right as God gives
us to see the right, let us
strive on to finish the
work we are in, to bind
up the nation's wounds,
to care for him who shall
have borne the battle and for his widow and
his orphan, to do all which may achieve
and cherish a just and lasting peace
among ourselves and with all nations.
- And we're all complicit
in this because we all
countenanced slavery. I mean, that's all
in that one speech. And it's a short
speech. The whole speech probably only
lasted eight or nine minutes. And he
also pays tribute to the citizen soldiers at
the beginning of it because he says that the
war is going well and we all know that
everything depends on what our soldiers do.
And by that he meant saving
the union, killing slavery, it
all depends on them. And then he comes back
and finishes with his tribute to the soldiers
at the end.
- And I have to say the Gettysburg Address.
- Oh, no, it's you can't.
- If I may, it's only maybe 200 words. Four
score and seven years ago, our fathers
brought forth on this
continent a new nation,
conceived in liberty and dedicated
to the proposition that all men
are created equal. Now we are engaged in a
great civil war, testing
whether that nation or
any nation so conceived and so dedicated
can long endure. We are met on a great
battlefield of that war. We have come
to dedicate a portion of that field as
a final resting place for
those who here gave their
lives that that nation might live.
It is altogether fitting and
proper that we should do this.
But in a larger sense, we cannot
dedicate, we cannot consecrate, we
cannot hallow this ground. The brave men
living and dead who struggled
here have consecrated it
far above our poor power
to add or detract.
The world will little note
nor long remember what
we say here, but it can
never forget what they did
here. It is for us the living,
rather, to be dedicated
here to the unfinished work
which they who fought here have
thus far so nobly advanced.
It is rather for us to be
here dedicated to the great
task remaining before us, that
from these honored dead we take increased
devotion to that cause for
which they here gave the
last full measure of
devotion, that we here highly
resolve that these dead
shall not have died in vain,
that this nation, under God, shall
have a new birth of freedom,
and that government of the people,
by the people, for the people shall
not perish from the earth.
That's a big statement about what this
country is about. It's about freedom.
- And he comes back to, when most people
read that, the very last part of it, they
emphasize the prepositions of the
people, by the people, for the people.
Lincoln, it's not about the
prepositions. It's about the people. He
earlier in the war referred to
this as a people's contest.
It's the people that are the key, the
people who make up the republic, the
people who will derive the freedoms and
liberties that the-- I mean,
it's an amazing-- and it
probably took you two minutes to read
that. He was finished before most people
knew he had started at Gettysburg. Almost
nobody heard him say that. The one
thing wrong about it is when he said no one
would remember very long what he said there.
It's been remembered pretty well.
- And let's talk about the two other figures
which we'll return to time and time again.
Ulysses S. Grant and Robert
E. Lee. So who was Grant?
So this is a man who failed at
farming. Failed at business,
failed at his role in the peacetime army.
Then when the war came, the war revealed a
genius.
- So he'd known a lot of failure,
he'd known a lot of setbacks, and
his wartime record shows that he'd learned
to deal with those things. He had a great,
tremendous relationship with his wife,
a very strong family life, a family he
loved. I think that was the rock for him.
But during the war, what he exhibited
was an absolute willingness
to break rules,
to take risks, to take responsibility
for what he was doing,
whether it was a success or a
failure, and not to be cast
down by things that didn't work. If something
didn't work, he'd say, "Okay, that didn't work.
Now let's do this." He very
famously, when he got to
Virginia in 1864 and took
over the Army of the Potomac,
he had all these subordinates who were
saying, "Well, what if General Lee does this?
What if General Lee does that?" He finally
said, "Why don't we start worrying-- let's--
not worrying about what General Lee is gonna
do and let General Lee worry about what
we're going to do?" I mean, he
just had... He was unflappable
under stress. He was the
perfect person to end up
heading the Union armies, and he and
Lincoln-- And Lincoln realized that,
and he proved indispensable. But he has
this reputation as a butcher, Grant the Butcher.
That's something that former Confederates
and some Democrats in the
North fastened on him. His
preferred way of fighting wasn't just
kind of slug it out. It's really
interesting to compare
his record in the war
and Lee's record in the war before
they wound up opposing each other
in Virginia in a really bloody
overland campaign. Grant's total
casualties in all his great battles
before they met were 37,000.
Lee's were over 98,000--
... in the same period. The bloodiest
general in US history by far in terms of
how many of his men get
shot is Robert E. Lee.
The most careful demographic
study of any Civil War army is
one done of Lee's army by a scholar
named Joe Glatthaar, and Joe figured out
that if you were a soldier in
Robert E. Lee's army, you had a 73%
chance of becoming a casualty. 73%.
Grant's casualties get high when he
runs into Robert E. Lee, just like
everybody else. So the butcher tag is
completely unfair about Grant.
He's also known as a drunk,
and people have gone back and forth
on that, whether he just had a
weakness, couldn't hold
his alcohol very well or
was okay as long as his wife was around and
he had a key staff officer to help him.
The point is, alcohol never got in the
way of anything Grant did during the
war, and he had
a superlative record of delivering victories
when the United States needed them,
and Lincoln figured that
out. And the absolute
proof of his stature because
of this is that in the March
of 1864, Congress decided to dust
off the rank of three-star general,
lieutenant general, and give it to
Grant. The only person who'd ever
had that rank was George Washington,
the man, Jorge. I mean, he
is the man. And so they
are saying, "Okay, Grant, you get
the rank the man had," and that
shows there's never been anyone else who
got it. You're the first. And then he would
also be the first to get a four-star
rank in the United States Army. That...
There couldn't be a
better indication of his
stature than that he got Washington's
rank. Winfield Scott had had it by brevet.
Grant got the actual rank.
- So in part, the Grant the Butcher
label was from the Overland
Campaign that we'll talk about-
- It is from the Overland Campaign
- ... as the military decisions made there.
- Yep.
- Uh, many would argue that those are
critically important for the success
of the war.
- Yes. He and Lee are often compared,
but for the last year of the war,
they're operating on it's not
apples to apples because Grant is
general in chief and is managing
the entire war effort. He's managing what
Sherman's doing and what Sheridan's doing
and what Nathaniel Bank...
Lee is an army commander.
He can recommend things to Jefferson Davis,
but he never commands more than an army,
and so he never operates at the level
that Grant did. Very late in the war, he
was made general in chief when it
was so late that it didn't matter.
- So who was Robert E. Lee? In April 1861,
Lee was offered command of the Union Army-
- He was
- ... and chose Virginia instead.
- He did.
- What was he actually choosing in that
decision? Was he choosing home? Was he
choosing honor? Was he choosing
slavery? And maybe just
zooming out, what do we need to understand
in the early steps about Robert
E. Lee? Who was the man?
- Well, Lee is sort of the antithesis
of Grant in some ways. Lee is from an
aristocratic family. Grant was from
a solidly middle-class family. Lee's
from an aristocratic
family at the very top
of the Virginia aristocracy. The
Lees are all... He has uncles who
were prominent, two signed the
Declaration of Independence. His
father was a famous commander under George
Washington. His father's the one who
said that Washington was first in war, first in
peace, first in the hearts of his countrymen.
That's Lee's father, who was later
a prominent Virginia politician.
Lee's idol is George
Washington. He patterns
himself on Washington. He differs
from him in some ways, but
he patterns himself on Washington.
He considered Washington the
most admirable person in United States
history. And then, of course, he almost
undoes the work that George Washington
put in place during the American
Revolution. He chose
Virginia. He didn't leave... He didn't resign
his commission in the United States Army
to go with the Confederacy. He resigned his
commission in the United States Army to,
to go to Virginia, which wasn't in the
Confederacy yet, become the head of state
forces in Virginia. But then
when Virginia went into the
Confederacy, he took his Confederate
commission and ended up as the
third-ranking officer in Confederate
service, and he makes an easy transition to
A Confederate loyalty. I think
it's his loyalty to Virginia
and what that means. That means his
family, and of course that means slavery.
That's part of what that loyalty is.
He's devoted to the slave-holding
South as well as to Virginia.
Virginia's a subset of that. All of
that is in one bundle
with Lee. It's all... But
th- he also had been an
ardent US nationalist
earlier in his career, and a very
successful military officer.
Winfield Scott thought he was the greatest soldier
in the army, and Scott, he probably really
thought, "Except for me." But Scott
is a great soldier that people don't
remember that way because he became a kinda
Jabba the Hutt figure by the time of the
Civil War. He's enormous, weighs 350
pounds, has to be winched onto his horse.
But he was a very smart guy
and he thought very highly
of Lee. Lee was a superb soldier,
as he would show during the war,
but he's on the wrong side.
- Maybe just to throw in a few
more characters, I do think
the folks on both sides that are the,
of the more radical persuasion are quite
interesting. Somebody you spoke about,
I'm not sure where, think it might've been
in your lecture series about Thaddeus
Stevens.
- Yes, the Thaddeus Stevens.
Thaddeus Stevens was one of the most
radical of the radical Republicans.
He's a congressman from Pennsylvania
who... People think people say harsh
things now in Congress. Thaddeus Stevens
just eviscerated people. And he was
way out... I mean, he was an ardent
abolitionist and for equal rights
for women in many ways and,
and he picked up a number of
causes and championed them.
- I think in your lecture you mentioned this
thing which I just love, the slime line.
- He had a-- This is his kind of
line. He's sitting in the House of
Representatives and one of his opponents-
... and he's speaking, and one of his opponents
starts to come down to the floor and he
says, and this is a paraphrase, "I'm
gonna pause while my colleague,"
from wherever he was from, "slinks
across the floor of this House and
adheres to his seat by his own slime."
- Yeah. Beautiful.
- That's a great line. Impromptu.
He had a... Women used to ask
for locks of hair as, from
famous people, and he was completely
bald and wore a full wig. He had
a woman stop him on the steps to the
Capitol and ask for a lock of his
hair, took his whole wig off and
said, "Madam, have them all." And c-
- Which is brilliant
- no, it's very good.
- But of the radical persuasion.
- Oh, absolutely. Yes, he defined it. He
is the character in Birth of a Nation
Stoneman, the character of Stoneman,
the evil radical Republican
named Stoneman, is patterned
on Thaddeus Stevens.
- All right. If we can, let's talk
about the buildup to the war.
- All right.
- What were the key states on
both sides that were debating?
What are the ones that
were certainly going to be
firmly on one side or the other?
And maybe what are the ones that
were critical at the, at the borderline?
- The states that were in the forefront of the
secession movement were the Deep South states, and
South Carolina was kind of ground
central for what was going
on there. It just so happened that
the Democrats had their national
convention in Charleston in 1860,
which is the worst place in the
world they could've had it if they wanted
a quiet, rational discussion of anything.
South Carolina is the first state to secede,
and then is quickly followed. You can
just go the tier across Alabama,
Mississippi, Florida, Georgia,
Texas. That's the... It's seven
states. The Deep South states go
out in that initial... But
there's a long period then,
and they gather in Montgomery, Alabama,
to establish a new government with
Montgomery as the capital
of the Confederacy.
Delegates from those states do. And
they set up a provisional government
that's gonna last a year and call
for the first national elections in
1861. There are only seven states
there, and really only six for a
lot of it 'cause Texas got there late.
It was the last of the first seven to
secede. But the states that haven't
seceded yet are the ones with
the most people. Virginia, which
is the most populous, North
Carolina, Tennessee,
Kentucky, Missouri. Eight
states have not gone out. Eight slaveholding
states have not gone out. The most
important one is Virginia
among those that-
... that have not gone
out. The question is,
can they find some resolution to
all of this, or is it gonna get
more serious, and are those states gonna
go? And it came to focus, once again, on
Charleston, South Carolina,
and a federal installation in
Charleston Harbor, Fort Sumter.
Much United States property and illic- and
installations had been just
given over to the Confederates.
And the question is, can we do it
with this one as well? This is a very
difficult decision to make, and
it comes down to what's gonna
happen in Charleston Harbor. And in the
end, I mean, Jefferson Davis believed
that he couldn't allow it to remain a
federal installation 'cause it's actually
in the Confederacy from their point
of view. And Lincoln, who's not
conceding the right of states to secede.
They're, they're temporarily out
of our power, but we have to maintain...
He decided in the end to maintain
power there, not to reinforce it,
but to resupply it, needed supplies.
And that's what triggers it. Then, then
the ball's in Jefferson Davis' court.
"Okay, they're gonna resupply it. What
do we do?" And they decided we need to
insist that it surrender, and if it won't
surrender, we need to fire on it. And
the Confederates fired the first shots. They
would've said, "We were forced to fire the
first shots by what Lincoln did." Nobody
wanted to be the ones who fired the first
shots. But in the end, it's the
Confederates who fired the first shots.
And once that is fired,
the key thing, the key
thing is not the firing
on Sumter in the end,
but that sets up the key
thing, which is Lincoln's call
for volunteers to suppress the
rebellion, and he is gonna ask each
state to supply people.
And the Upper South states, most of them
have said, "We're not gonna secede, but
you can't... But, but the states that
are gone had the right to secede-
... and you can't do anything to make
them come back." Lincoln is seeming to
make them do things to come back.
And so four more states went out.
Virginia went out. Arkansas
went out. Tennessee went out.
Then North Carolina went out. And
now you have an 11-state Confederacy
rather than seven. But more
than that, you have Virginia.
The city of Richmond has 40% of all
the industrial capacity in the entire
Confederacy, what became the Confederacy.
Virginia is the most populous state, has
the largest slave population,
the largest white population.
It supplies the most important
military leaders. And the
capital ends up in Richmond. They
move from Montgomery to Richmond
in acknowledgment of how important
Richmond is, that this is the key
state. The key states that didn't
go out were Maryland, Kentucky,
and Missouri. Delaware didn't either, but who
cares? The other three didn't go out, and that
really mattered because they were
more populous. But 11 are gone.
Four remain in the Union.
- And to lay out some more context,
going to Perplexity here,
by total enslaved population
on the eve of the Civil War,
we have looking at the top
five states, Virginia,
as you said, with the most
number of slaves, 490,000.
Then Georgia, Mississippi, Alabama, South
Carolina, all with over 400,000 slaves.
- Yes. And Mississippi and South Carolina
have the highest proportion of
enslaved people of any of
the states. And this is an
interesting little fact from the 1860 census.
When you're talking about white people in the
United States, those are the two wealthiest
states per capita in the United States,
are South Carolina and
Mississippi in 1860.
- Boy, the complicated history
of this great nation of ours.
- It's hard to overstate the resources.
The states that sent the most men
into the Confederate Army are Virginia,
Tennessee, North Carolina,
and Georgia. Three of those
come in this second wave of secessions.
Three of them, three of the four. Only
Georgia among the original ones was in those
top four states. And so you would have had a
much, much smaller pool
of manpower for that
earlier version of the Confederacy. It's
inconceivable to me that you would have
had the war we had with just that version.
- So it does feel, just to linger on it,
like there was a lot on the
balance here. Like there was a
lot of different decisions
that could have been made,
even on the political side, that
could have turned the tides.
- For example, there's a secession
convention in Virginia.
It goes in... It votes
twice against secession.
Twice. It's only after Sumter that
they come back for another vote.
I mean, it's a Unionist vote in
that convention in Virginia.
And it's only after Fort Sumter.
- Wow.
- And then it's still so divided
that a big chunk of Virginia
decide that's how you get West
Virginia. West Virginia essentially
secedes from Virginia- ... in
the course of the Civil War.
- And given the industrial capacity of Virginia, that
was a critical state. So it could have been...
Virginia could have changed. We could
have avoided the Civil War with
Virginia alone.
- It would have really changed. I mean,
Virginia is the key. Virginia is the key
because of the manpower, the industrial
capacity, the food production,
and Virginia gives you Lee, Jackson, Jeb
Stuart. I mean, it, and the most
soldiers of any state in the
Confederacy. It's just, it's a real game
changer to get Virginia.
Plus, it also gives you these
unbelievable ties to the revolutionary
generation. Hey, it's George's
home state. It is now in the
Confederacy with his big statue
on the Capitol grounds of George Washington.
I mean, gives you, you get Washington, the
ties to Jefferson, the ties to Madison.
All of this comes in with Virginia.
- So I think a lot of historians have
said that the Civil War was inevitable.
It... You're really painting a picture
here where it perhaps was not inevitable.
- I don't think it's inevitable. Things
happen in a sequence. I was at a
conf- academic conference once when they were
trying to decide what important dates were,
and one... And they concluded
that no dates are, dates are an
artificial construction. No date
is more important than any other.
That is so obviously
preposterous. I mean, things
happen in a sequence. They don't just
sort of happen. Lincoln's elected,
then South Carolina secedes, then other
states secede, then... I mean, things
happen as a consequence of what happened
before, and you have these various
things that have to happen
before the next thing does. And
then we end up with a war
that seems to be inevitable,
but it's not... It's just the way things
played out. All of these factors are in
motion, and you end up with the sequence that gets
you to where people start shooting each other.
- Yeah. When you read history and look back,
it seems inevitable. But if we were to
place ourselves in that moment of time, do
you think there's decisions that could have
been made?
- The decision to not let Fort
Sumter, I mean, that's a
big decision to make. If they had just, if Lincoln
had just said, "Go ahead and take Fort Sumter,"
okay, then maybe... Then what
would it have taken to trigger
the departure of those upper South states?
That would have changed that whole equation.
But Lincoln decided you
just can't keep giving them
everything that they want if you don't concede
that they have the right to do what they did.
- Yeah, there would be a
continued heated political
debates, intense political debates
about the expansion of slavery, but it
would not cause rebellion to then
escalate into a full-on hot war.
- I think that's conceivable. I don't
think the war was inevitable. I think it
But I think the conditions were
present for it to happen, obviously.
I mean, that's stating... 'Cause
it did happen. But I think it's
very tricky to just say that
it was inevitable. That's kind
of starting at the end of the story and just saying,
"Let's look at the factors that got us here.
We know it was gonna happen, and these are
the things that pointed this direction."
- Can we just actually linger on this, on the
nature of war? Over 700,000 people dead.
How do we make sense of our capacity
as, in that context, Americans?
To kill sometimes literally our brothers
- Yes, sometimes literally our brothers
- How is that even possible?
- Well, one thing, it tells me things are pretty
important to people on both sides if you're
gonna continue for a war that long.
I mean, there was a period in the
literature, in the scholarly literature
in the 1980s and into the 1990s where
they argued that the Confederacy
wasn't a nation, and the proof was that they didn't
try very hard, that they... If they'd really
thought of themselves as a nation, they
would have tried harder and fought longer.
Well, they lost between four and a half
and five and a half percent of their
entire population, which is more
than Great Britain, France, Germany,
or Russia during World War I. They
had a higher percentage loss than any
of the powers in World War I. The US lost
about 1.8% of its population from the war.
US, in World War II, three-tenths of
1% of its population... That seems...
They lost more than 30% of
their entire white military-age
males in the war. It'd be the equivalent
of about 18 million Americans being killed
now in a war. That seems to me that they're
pretty serious about something there.
- It means that's one of the
largest percentages of loss.
That's... If that's a
measure of dedication-
- If that's your measure of dedication,
yes, and it seems to me that it should be
one of the metrics that you bring to
play that, that it's... They just keep
at it. They didn't give up easily.
- What can we say about the motivation?
On the psychological side, did the
members of the Confederacy
hate the members of the Union?
- Well, that escalated on both sides during
the war. As more and more loss came,
you... They did. There was more hatred
directed toward the enemy more and more.
This notion that it's they're all brothers
and not really mad at each other and...
That just doesn't hold up. There are
places where the soldiers fraternized
with one another and traded tobacco for
coffee and that kind of
stuff, but no, the bitterness
as the war went on, and there was greater
loss on the home front, and as the
war became more all-encompassing
and really went after the entire,
The civilian side of the Confederacy
was not shielded from it, the
bitterness increased and increased
and increased. And there's a
lot of unhappiness with the war
behind the lines in the Confederacy,
absolutely, unhappiness with the
government. There's desertion.
About 15% of Confederate
soldiers deserted.
About 12% of United States
soldiers deserted. So there's
desertion on both sides.
There's war-weariness,
but the war goes on because I think if
you had been able to poll most white
Southerners even late in the war and
say, "Okay, here are your choices.
You either have Jefferson Davis in the government
and the war goes on, or you're going back
into the United States and the Lincoln
government will be in charge and you won't have
slavery. Which one do you pick?" They're
gonna pick the first one, and that's why
the war went on as long as it did.
- But at the same time, to fast-forward,
and that maybe teaches you something about
the nature of war, but after the war,
maybe some of the decisions that
Grant made, people were able to
rediscover the brotherhood.
- You mean at Appomattox
you're talking about-
- Appomattox
- ... the terms at Appomattox.
- Yes.
- Yes, the... And those
were... And he didn't just
reach up in the air and say, "I've got some
terms." The... Lincoln very specifically...
He met with Lincoln shortly before
Appomattox. Sherman was there.
One top naval officer was there, Grant
and Lincoln, and Lincoln said, "This is
what I want. This is the
kind of peace I want."
"The whole point of this war is to put
the nation back together, and a good
start on that is..."
I mean, if it's just a rebellion, what
do you do with traitors and rebels?
You hang them.
You don't bring them back. You don't treat them
as prisoners of war, which the United States
did during this. You, he... But the goal is
to put the nation back together, and Lincoln
said, "This is a good start. Make
them sign a parole. Make them accept
the end of slavery and the fact that they're back
in the Union. If they do that, they get to go
home and resume their lives." Hadn't
been decided yet whether they'll get to
vote, but let them go home. Don't
imprison them. Don't execute
them. Don't execute their
leaders. That's the decision.
- From the perspective of the Union, what do
you think about that kind of forgiveness?
- Well, I think that it was sort
of a nod toward the direction of
forgiveness, but I don't think the real...
I don't think real forgiveness was there.
It was still extremely hard feelings
on both sides, and Lincoln's
assassination upped the ante on
that, especially for a while,
in the United States.
The, the forgiveness...
Two things in terms of the aftermath of
the war, two words that often come into
play are reunion and reconciliation.
Those are two other things that are
often conflated. Reunion is literally
putting the nation back together.
That happened. Reconcile, true
reconciliation, that's much, much,
much tougher, and that didn't
come anytime soon on the part of millions
of people on both sides, I think.
- And we'll probably maybe talk about
in multiple ways how maybe that is
something that's still going on.
- Oh, there are echoes of the Civil War all
over the place. It's not still being fought,
but you can see resonances of the
Civil War because it's such a
profoundly disruptive
event that gets right
at the heart of what the republic means.
I mean, and so it's... There's nothing
else like it in US history, and
it's a great moment of truth,
the residual aftermath and
effects of which lingered for
decades and are still present
in some ways, I think.
- So in 1859, most Americans
were just living their life.
Did they have a sense
what was on the horizon?
- It's what I like to call the Appomattox
Syndrome, which starts at the end of the story
And says, "Of course there was gonna be a war
because the war was inevitable, and of course the
United States was gonna win and slavery was
gonna be destroyed," because they were.
So let's find out how we got right here.
But no, most people didn't
wake up in Iowa in 1857
and their first thought was,
"Boy, I hate the South."
"Those slaveholders, they're really..."
No. People got on with their
quotidian lives and they got to the
farm or they went to their business and
they did... They weren't... Nobody
knew that they were living in the
antebellum era, and that those great
antebellum years were about to come to an end.
They... That is something that
it's hard to get people not...
To just put it out of your mind that that's all
anybody is thinking about. They're thinking,
"There's a lot of other stuff going on."
There's a big gold rush in Colorado.
More people go to Colorado than went to
California for a while.
There is... And you have
these tremendous changes coming about,
technological changes of the 1850s
where you have the real expansion of
railroads, the real expansion of the
telegraph. There's a shrinking of time and
space that's remarkable for people
at the time. It seemed dizzying
to them at the time. There are a lot of things
to think about other than how much I hate
Yankees if I'm in South Carolina, or I hate
slaveholders if I live in New Hampshire.
But periodically, there are
these events that pop up that
refocus on the differences
between the sections.
And you have the Kansas-Nebraska
Act. You have Dred
Scott. You have the caning of Charles
Sumner on the floor of the Senate.
You have Uncle Tom's Cabin earlier
in the decade in 18-- and what...
And the impact that that had on attitudes
towards slavery. Doesn't create a bunch of
abolitionists, but it creates a
bunch of people who rethink their
thoughts about slavery.
- Sorry to ask the big
question about history. But,
you know, we're living today, 2026,
and there's the sense that
every day you wake up,
the possibilities before us are endless,
for the good, for the bad, for
the truly destructive. There's a
an eerie sense that the possibility of
a world war in different kinds of ways,
whether it's sparked in the Middle East or
sparked in China and Taiwan, or sparked
in Ukraine-Russia,
or elsewhere totally surprising in
the world, may be related to nuclear
weapons or not. There's a sense
that everything is possible.
And of course, when history is
written about the 21st century,
it will all be obvious.
- It's always obvious in
retrospect. That's right.
- What can we learn about... from the
Civil War about how history unfolds
itself, I suppose, for the modern day?
- Well, I think that the
potential threats now
are different from the potential threats in
the mid-19th century. The nuclear dimension,
some kind of really brutal use of
pathogens. I mean, there are lots of
things that could happen now that couldn't
happen then, at least not because humans
were making them happen. But I mean, to,
to me, one of the things to take away from
the Civil War is really the resiliency
of this republic, which I
still think it's a resilient
republic. We're living
in a sort of wacky time.
Uh, but I believe that
the... I think that...
I have a great faith in the
resiliency of the nation, I really
do, of the United States. I think it's been
through much tougher times than we're in now,
and I think that we will weather
this, although everybody
will have some scar tissue.
There might even come a
time when our leadership class
actually leads, and which would be
interesting. And I'm saying, you
know, I'm talking about both
sides of the fence here.
But it is... That, to me,
this is, this is the supreme test
of a republic that had been put in
place in the late 18th century. Can
that late 18th century republic
adjust, including adjusting
to deal with the profoundly
disruptive issue of slavery,
in a way that allows it
to go forward? And the answer
is yes. In a war that brings
slaughter on an unimaginable scale and
brings social disruption in the former
slave-holding states on an unimaginable...
It just couldn't be more profoundly
disruptive if you're a
Confederate. There's not slavery
anymore, and we lost the war, and a third
of our military-age white men are dead.
Wow, that's a bad four years
for our team. What's gonna
happen here? The Republic emerged from
that and worked it out, and I think it
is... It goes back to, to me,
the intelligence of the founding generation
that put in place documents that
actually allowed the Republic to
deal with something like this.
And it's sort of a miracle to me
that from a nation that was
as prejudiced, racially
prejudiced as the United
States was, you get the 13th,
14th, and 15th Amendments out
of this. It's just kind of
mind-boggling that that happens.
- Yeah, I think resilience and
adaptive innovation often looks
like chaos in the moment.
- It absolutely does. It absolutely
does. But then when you really get
to the end of that story, you look, and
there you are, and oh, it's okay, the
nation is still intact. And the 13th
Amendment is in place. Wow, we didn't think-
... that was gonna happen in 1861-
... when secession started. I mean, it
really... One, another lesson is that you
cannot control what a great
military event can set loose.
I mean, no, things that nobody imagined
would happen, including expansion of
central power
in ways that no one would have imagined. You don't
get to ratchet that back and say, "Well, that'll
never happen again." No, you know what? It happened,
and maybe it will happen again because we've
seen it happen. Nobody imagined
that. The federal budget in
1860 was $63 million. That was
the entire federal budget.
The federal budget in 1865
was $1.2 billion, and
if you throw in the Confederate side of that,
it gets you over $2 billion, which means
federal expenditures in 1860 would've
lasted about 11 days in 1865. Nobody
foresaw that. Absolutely
nobody foresaw that. And
education legislation that would create
the great land grant colleges and
universities and no- it's...
The war brought a lot
- And I think most of the things that have
happened through the hard periods of our
country's history, nobody
could have really f-
foreseen, and then we somehow figure it
out, and that gives me a lot of hope.
- We-
- That this kinda like extreme
division, the arguments, the people
basically speaking in the harshest
of ways against each other,
that is like the engine of,
brainstorming and figuring problems out
that in the long arc of history create
progress. But in the short term,
it feels like a dumpster fire.
- It does. And to me, the arc of US history
has been, and Lincoln talked about this
too, it's an expansion of freedoms and
liberties. That's the,
that's the long arc,
with very problematical
places along the way. But
again, the documents allow for
that, and the process allows
for that, and I think that's one
of the remarkable things about
Philadelphia in the summer of 1787. I mean,
those guys, a lot of whom own slaves,
put together something that's proved to be
resilient and adaptable and changeable,
and it has evolved in a way that is in
the right direction, although there are
always problems.
- I love this country. I
will never stop saying how
much I love this country. It's
an incredible experiment.
I'm... we're this year celebrating its
250th birthday. I can't wait for the next
250 years. This is such a fascinating
study of human civilization.
- And it is complicated. What we want now
is a sort of cartoon version of what we
Americans, as you watch
popular culture, we want a
30-second view of whatever. Well, who should I
like? Who are the good guys? Who are the bad
guys? I want a 30-second version
of the Civil War. What do I...
History is not that way.
I've spent my whole life
studying history, and the maybe the main
thing I've learned is however complicated
I thought something was when I really started
to explore it, it's more complicated than
I thought it was. People aren't simple.
They're complicated. And you have to
at least
appreciate, you don't have to embrace the
complexity. I guess you can't make people do that,
but you have to at least concede that
things are... they're just... There's not a
20-second version of anything in
the past. The past is complicated,
because humanoids are involved
in it. They're complicated.
- Yeah, the... when you look at the system
as a whole. But as individual humans, we
like to do the black
and white thing where-
- Of course.
- ... we just see the good, everything
as good and evil, and then we bicker.
- 'Cause it's easier.
- And then we get together at Thanksgiving dinner,
and we yell at each other, and then people lose
their shit, and they stop talking to
each other for a year, and then they,
they make up and all this 'cause this is
just how humans interact with each other.
And, but as a system, especially
with the increasing levels of
freedom, with the freedoms of
speech and be able to speak out
about your feelings, even when they're
intense feelings, that somehow works as a
system.
- And it's very messy.
- Yeah, yeah.
- The more freedom, the messier it
is. Really, the messier it is.
- And your job as a historian
is a difficult job, and as you
said, because the more you learn,
the more you come to understand, the
more complicated the picture appears.
- Yep, and the more you learn, the more you
learn that you don't know as much as you
thought you did.
- So some humility will take you a long way.
- Yes, you want more of Grant,
than McClellan in that, on that
humility score. Grant would
score high on humility. McClellan,
every day, every day the first
thought was, "What about me?"
"Who is gonna not appreciate how wonderful
I am today?" thought George B. McClellan.
That's the thought that nagged at him.
"Somebody might not know how great I am."
That's an aside.
- Reminds me of somebody. But anyway.
Quick ten-second shout-out to our sponsors.
Check them out in the description.
It really is the best way to
support this podcast. Go to
lexfridman.com/sponsors. And now, dear
friends, back to my conversation
with Gary Gallagher.
Okay, let's at the start, first shots
fired at Fort Sumter, as you mentioned,
and this thing starts brewing and
escalating towards a full-on war.
What are the different advantages of
each side from a military perspective?
- Here is one of the great misconceptions about
the Civil War. Among the people who know
anything about it, which in the
US is a very small percentage,
but if they know anything, they know
United States' victory was inevitable.
Because the United States
had 22 million people.
The Confederacy had five and
a half million white people-
... and three and a half million
enslaved people. The United States'
economy was infinitely
more powerful than the
Confederate economy. The United States
had the United States Army. The United
States had the United States Navy.
Really, who's gonna win this war?
The US, it's inevitable, next
question. It's not true at all. The
US did have those advantages, but the
Confederacy had compensating
advantages. And
one of those advantages was
it had a much lower bar to
cross for success. It didn't have
to invade the United States,
didn't have to capture Washington. It
didn't have to project its military
power into New England. All it
had to do was convince a majority
of the civilian population
of the loyal states that it
wasn't worth the cost to make
these rebel states come back into
the Union. These are two democratic
republics at war, and in
the end, the civilian sector
decides. Somebody my age
can... We have the perfect example,
Vietnam. The United States was
not defeated militarily in
Vietnam, and it didn't matter.
'Cause when the people said, "We're not gonna
support this war anymore," the war's gonna come to
an end. The smart people in the
Confederacy understood this. They
understood it at the time. Lee understood
it. Jefferson Davis understood it.
You had key people at the time
saying, "There's no way that a
nation as large as ours and a population
as large as ours has ever been
subjected in a war like this.
A tie is as good as a win for the
Confederacy." And they came very close to
that in the summer of 1864. The
other thing is the sheer size
of the Confederacy is a huge
advantage to them. It's huge, with
a very poor transportation and
communication infrastructure in
many ways. And to move a large army
deep into the Confederacy is
a huge logistical problem.
The same thing had happened to the British both
during the American Revolution and the War of
1812. They confront this... The Confederacy's
as big as all of Western Europe.
That's a problem. It's also a problem
that the Confederates are fighting,
literally fighting to defend their
homes. That's always, almost
always a stronger factor
than trying to impose your
will on somebody else. All of these
factors help the Confederacy.
The US did have an army. The
army had 15,000 men in it in
1860, 15,000. The Navy had
fewer than 50 vessels,
most of them on overseas
stations. There were exactly
three vessels available to blockade
the Confederacy at the beginning
of the war. The Confederate coastline's
3,600 miles long. Probably not gonna be
able to shut down a lot there.
So the point is that there are
factors that help both sides. To me, the
conditions for victory are the most important
factor that favors the Confederacy.
We just have to make it painful
enough to the United States
that they're gonna say, "Let them go. We
never liked South Carolina anyway. Just
let them go. We're not... It's not worth it. It's
killing too many of our boys. It's costing too
much money, and we don't have to worry about
slavery in the territories if they're gone,
'cause they'll be gone. And our
territories will be free of slavery."
- So again, the Union is the invading force.
- Yes.
- Geography comes into
play, as you mentioned.
- Immediately, yes.
- Vast land. And so in some
sense, it's a miracle
that the war lasted as long as it did,
and then there was as much motivation-
- Yes, that they stuck to it
- ... because again, victory for
the Confederacy was stop the war.
- Stop the war. Neither side has
an advantage in terms of its
leadership. The generals
all come... You often
used to read frequently Confederates had
better generals than the... And, but
this is the first war where West-- where
West Pointers are in charge. They were
subalterns in Mexico. The West Point is the
United States Military Academy where the
professional officer corps gets its training.
It was established under Jefferson.
It's the premier engineering school in
the United States. And I mean, West
Point-trained engineers are very, very
prominent when they get out of the
army and even when they're in the
army. But by the time of the Civil
War, it is West Pointers
who were lieutenants and
captains in the war with Mexico
are now gonna be the people in
charge. Almost every army commander,
almost every corps commander, which
is the next level,
are West Point graduates. They took
the same classes from the same
professors, read the same textbooks,
served under either Winfield
Scott or Zachary Taylor in Mexico.
They bring the same background
and body of doctrine and
training to the table.
It would've been weird if one
side or the other had an inherent
advantage in leadership. The one
place where the US ends up with an
advantage is that over the course
of the war, it found, in my
view, four men who could command
armies effectively: Grant,
Sherman, Philip Henry Sheridan, and
George H. Thomas. The Confederacy
only ever found one, and that's
Lee. And they had more than one
army, so that's a problem. If you have more
than one army but only one really good army
commander, that puts
you at a disadvantage.
- In what ways were the two
sides balanced militarily,
Equal militarily? So the, the
passion, like we mentioned,
of the fighting force, the soldiers,
the dedication to the fighting.
- Both brought the same notions of how to
fight a war to the table because the
officer corps had been, on both
sides, had been trained in the
same way. Neither side has
a real advantage in terms
of technology. Both sides
use the railroad. Both
sides use the telegraph. The United States
could have used repeating weapons but
decided not to. The Confederacy didn't
have the industrial capacity to
produce. So the war is fought by
infantrymen, for the most part,
carrying muzzle-loading single-shot
muskets, rifle muskets.
That's the weapon that inflicts
85 to 90% of the casualties-
... in the Civil War, and they both
have exactly the same thing. And they
have the same kinds of artillery
pieces. The United States
Navy's much bigger, but it's...
And the Navy is important,
but armies really decide the war,
and the armies are... They're
organized exactly the same way.
They are-- They get officers the
same way. They're very similar.
- So what was the actual fighting like?
Like you mentioned, most of it was with
muskets. What was the
experience of it like?
- It's linear formations,
shoulder-to-shoulder kinds of formations
that would allow you to
maintain unit integrity on a
battlefield, which is one reason
casualties were high. They'd line up and
fight each other.
As the war went on, they resorted more
and more. One of the developments
was the field entrenchments
became very common by
1864. And both armies, if they would
stop for the night, they would entrench.
They'd throw up field works--
... which gave the defenders a
much greater power vis-a-vis
the attacking force. They came to
decide that you needed about a
three-to-one advantage in numbers to
have a successful attack once field
entrenchments were in place. But
it is... It's an infantryman's war
overwhelmingly, and the infantryman's
experience on both sides. The United States
side was a little better supplied.
Union soldiers ate a little
better for the most part.
They got regular issues
of clothing a little more regularly than the
Confederates did. Their uniforms all kind of looked
the same. The Confederates would
have had a more motley look.
But the Confederates didn't lose any
battles because they didn't have enough
shoes, and they didn't lose any battles 'cause
they didn't have enough powder. They never had
a problem with that. So it's
a war where each side looks
like the other side in terms of what the
armies actually... If we had wandered
through the armies and, or watched
them in battle, they would have looked
the same to us.
- But it wasn't just about bullets.
There was also dysentery and disease.
- Two out of every three soldiers
who died, died of disease.
It depends on what unit you're in. If you're
in the Irish Brigade, ah, God love them.
You know, just point us towards
something and let us indulge in
self-immolation, for God's
sake. The Irish Brigade had the
reverse. They had two men who died
from battle wounds for every man who
died from disease. But overall, it's
one man died from battle wounds
and two died from disease. Overall
casualties, killed, wounded,
prisoners of war, about a million and a
half-- ... casualties in the Civil War.
- There-- You know, there's this idea that
a big part of the American spirit is the
Scots-Irish spirit, the fighting spirit.
You think there's some truth to that?
- Well, the songs are Irish songs that
both sides sing with different words,
and I mean, there are a lot of
Irish soldiers in the Union Army.
But in the entire military-age
white population of
the loyal states in
1860, just about a third
were born somewhere other
than the United States.
And they made up about a quarter of
all the soldiers. So they're actually
underrepresented in the United States
Army. Far lower percentage of foreign-born
soldiers in the Confederate Army, but there
they're a little bit overrepresented.
So there are lots of foreign-born
soldiers in the army. The
largest group are not Irish. They're the second
largest group. The largest group are Germans,
On the US side. The Irish are second,
and then you'd go way down the
line for yet others.
- So we talked pretty thoroughly about
slavery. Can we talk about immigration?
What was the view at
the time of immigrants?
- Well,
I think you know the answer to that. We
need to have all that stuff done, but we
don't especially like the people doing
it. That's basically the... Well,
I mean, the--
- Oh, America
- ...the anti-Irish, and a lot of
it is bound up with anti-Catholic
sentiment. The-- 'Cause the Irish are
changing the nature of the country.
The country's a Protestant,
British country, and here come all
these Irishmen. And especially in
the '40s and '50s, the-- My
Gallaghers came in the late '50s.
They are changing the nature, and they
take over. Look at them. They don't know
their place. They're--
... pretty soon they're taking over cities, and
they all cheat when they vote. We know that.
You can buy an Irish vote for one drink.
- This all sounds familiar, right?
- The cartoons were brutal on depicting
African American characters, but they also
depicted the Irish as sort of simian
characters, often with a jug of
whiskey in one hand. I mean, it's
very... There's profound prejudice. And
prejudice against the Germans, whom
they called the Dutch. That was what
the soldiers would call the German
regiments, Dutch regiments. And
yeah, there's a lot of ethnic prejudice.
- So to mention, you mentioned
Protestants, so both sides were
primarily Protestant Christians.
- Overwhelmingly.
- At that time, it was a
very religious country.
- Yes, yes.
- So the religious sentiment
was pretty strong.
- Units had chaplains, and there
were Catholic priests with
Catholic units. Yes, a very big presence.
- Was Christianity used to justify--
- Of course it was. Both sides used it, yes.
I don't mean to jump on your
question, but yes, they did.
- I mean, how was it used to
justify fighting for a nation?
- Yeah, there's a lot of fighting in the Bible,
a lot of people killing other people in
the Bible-- As long as you're
doing it for the right reasons--
- Right.
- ...you can... And you could use it
different ways. I mean, you can deal with
setbacks by saying, "Well, God tests
us. We're being tested." What do you
do when God tests you? You don't give up when God
tests you. You try harder when God tests you.
The very top leaders... This is
interesting. The top leaders
on the Confederate side, the most famous
ones, Lee, Stonewall Jackson, Jeb Stuart,
they were much more overtly
religious than people like
Grant, Sherman, Philip Sheridan.
I mean, much, much more. Lee,
was an Episcopalian. Jackson was a
Presbyterian. But they talked-- I mean, their
official reports, their correspondence,
it's filled with allusions to
religion much more than
Grant's or Sherman's.
- What about African Americans in the army?
- African Americans made up... There
were about 200,000 Black men
served in what were called United
States Colored Troops units, USCT.
- It was on the Union side.
- On the U- Yes. Okay, let's
just dispense with the
hallucination that there were a lot
of Black men in the Confederate Army.
That is such total- Ridiculous nonsense-
... utterly unsupported by any evidence
that anyone would consider credible.
This whole notion of... I mean,
it's just, it's preposterous.
It's ridic- and I'm really
managing my language right here.
I'm not saying what I really
think it is. So, so just... I've
seen estimates of as high as 100,000
Black men in the Confederate Army.
- Not true.
- Really, really, no.
No. Were there Black men with the
Confederate armies? Yes. There are enslaved
Black men who are doing all kinds
of non-military things in the army
to free more white men to shoulder
muskets and shoot at Yankees.
That's what's going on in the Confederate
Army. There are a lot of Black men around
Union armies before they became soldiers
as well. But there are these...
200,000 Black men join the military service
during the war. They're in the Navy and in the
Army. They'd always been in the
Navy. The US Navy... And they're
not segregated in the Navy in the, in the way
that they can be in the Army. They're just in
Bl- you have integrated crews-
... on naval vessels, although they're separated
in some ways, but there've always been
Black sailors in the Navy.
The Army, no. That was
a big, it's a big thing to
put Black men in uniform. And
for a Confederate, it's bad enough if
you announce emancipation, but you, then
you start arming Black men.
That, to Confederates,
is urging a widespread
slave rebellion, basically.
- Black regiments on the Union side
was enraging the Confederate side.
- Yes. And they have white officers
overwhelmingly. There are a few
Black officers, but overwhelmingly the USCT
units have white officers leading them.
- But symbolically, that is a
really powerful thing, right?
- Oh, it's hard for modern
Americans to understand just how
jarring that would be to a Confederate,
that not only would you have enslaved
people no longer enslaved, but you would
have the men in uniforms carrying muskets.
- So you as a historian, you've looked at
every layer of this, including diaries and-
- What, what was motivating?
What was going through the
minds of African Americans who
were fighting for the Union side?
I think what you would expect is going... I mean, they
would talk about Union occasionally, but what that
means to them, it's a union without
slavery. They have the most... Of
all the people who can have a direct
impact on what's going on versus slavery,
there's nothing more direct than picking up a
musket and firing at the people
who are defending a slavery-based
society. It doesn't get... And at the
same time, you are not only doing that,
you are also establishing an
unimpeachable claim to citizenship. The
whole point of a citizen soldier
is that you do your bit for the
nation that's helping you, and the
nation does these things for you.
Well, okay, if I'm picking up and risking my life
with a musket in my hand, are you gonna tell
me I can't vote after I do? I thought
that's the whole point of this, when I'm
protecting the right to vote by doing
my citizen's role as a soldier.
And that was a big debate in Congress.
That really changed the equation of that
debate as well. How are you gonna treat
people after they've served
in United States units?
Can you tell them they can't vote?
You're not gonna give the vote to them?
- How many people in the Black regiments,
but also, you know, folks like Frederick
Douglass, saw that Black Americans and
white Americans should have equal rights?
- Well, Douglass saw that, of course. But
even within their context, their notion
of equal rights is that that doesn't mean that
Black women are gonna vote, just like for white
people, it didn't mean white women would
vote. But in terms of the context of the
time, yes,
equal rights should come out of this.
Abolishing slavery is the first step of this.
It's not the end game. The end game
is equal rights for everybody.
- Did many people see that?
- No. A tiny percentage of people
saw that. There's a notion
that's very common that somehow
the white North turned its back
on Black people after the war, and it
should've tried harder during Reconstruction
to force the white South to convey
full equal rights to Black people.
The assumption there is simply
flawed. Most white people in the
North didn't believe that... They believed
first save the Union, and yes, we'll need
to kill slavery as well. Those are the two
things on the list. Check, check, we've done
those. Full equal rights for Black people is
not on their list. That... And they were not
willing to do the things that it would've taken to
do that, including the white
soldiers in uniforms who
wanted out of the army after the Confederates
surrendered and said, "Well, now we
need the army to make the white South do
the right thing vis-à-vis Black people."
They would've said, "What
are you talking about?"
"I signed on to do this. We did
it. Send us home right now."
- I think that's one of the lessons you learn
from human history across the different
places where slavery was abolished,
is abolishing slavery is not the end of a
journey. It's the beginning of a journey.
- It's the beginning.
- And it sometimes takes, quite
often takes at least 100 years
to go from that to something you
would identify as equal rights.
And then maybe even beyond that,
there's a complicated story about
even outside of rights, just how
society sees the different people.
- There's a difference between passing...
I mean, the Great Society passed most of
the... I mean, you got the Civil Rights Act,
the Voting Rights Act, the Fair Housing Act.
You got all of this legislation that does
a lot of the legal stuff, but it's what's
in people's heads- ... that takes longer
and is a, is a more frustrating process.
- Remains, as has appeared in
human history, potential fuel
for the division to rise up again.
- Of course. And then people can exploit
that. It's, it's waiting to be
exploited, and people exploit it.
- This is something we do as humans.
We like to otherize certain groups.
- Good to have an enemy.
- And the Civil War for our country
is a story of this. It's...
So understanding the Civil War
is in part extremely important
for understanding the, the division,
maybe the dormant division that's there.
- Yes. And there, and even
before the war, there were-
There were notions about the
other side that sort-- for,
for a lot of people in the free states
looking South, they said white Southerners
are because of they're lazy, they're
violent, they, they don't wanna
talk out a problem. They'll do
what Preston Brooks did to Charles Sumner.
They'll beat him over the head with a
cane, and they're used to this because
they have slavery, and they're used to
brutalizing Black people. That's just
how they approach things. And the white
South would look North and say they don't care
anything about family. They're all just lusting
after money. All they care about is
material things. They don't have any
sense of kinship or family.
They're... That's what Yankees
are. It doesn't even matter whether
any of that is true, of course.
There was a sense perceptions are more
important than reality with human
beings, and the perceptions on the eve
of the Civil War were that the other
side was different in a lot of
ways. They also had profoundly
profound commonalities. They
had a common language, a common
religion, a common history,
these founding documents. All of
that would pull things,
pull people together.
But they found ways to see
differences and divided
some of the churches. I mean, Protestant
churches divided over slavery.
- And many of these themes
continue to today. Let's
talk about the different theaters of the war,
the Eastern Theater and the Western Theater.
You mentioned the navies, the geography. How
does geography come into play? What are the
different parts here?
- There's three main theaters of the war.
The Eastern Theater is the theater
that features Washington and Richmond.
Plays out in Virginia, a little bit of
Maryland, and a little bit of Pennsylvania.
That's-- it's where the Army of Northern Virginia
and the Army of the Potomac fight for the most
part. That's the Eastern Theater.
- And that's the theater that maybe
is most glorified and mythologized.
- It's by far the most
famous of the theaters.
There are famous battles in the other theaters,
but that's the one, and it's mainly because of the
presence of Lee and then of Grant.
The Western Theater is a much larger one.
It goes from the Appalachian Mountains
to the Mississippi River,
east to west, and would go
from the Gulf to the Ohio River, so it's
huge and involves Tennessee and, and then
beyond the Mississippi River
is the descriptively named
Trans-Mississippi River, part of Louisiana,
Arkansas, Texas, and so forth. In terms
of commitment of resources and
effect on the outcome of the war,
it's by far the least important. Some
people get very upset when I say that,
say that, that the Trans-- you know, it's basically
who cares about what's going on out there.
But that's the third theater, the
Trans-Mississippi, the Western Theater,
and the Eastern Theater.
- But I think you've argued that the Western
Theater is really important for the war.
- Very important, and it's
where we get Grant. The
soldiers who won the war
for the United States
all come out of the Western
Theater. Grant, he brings
Sherman, Philip Sheridan, George Thomas.
Those are all in the Western Theater.
- So at the very beginning, the first real
battle, at the First Manassas in July
1861, I think one
interesting aspect of that,
as you've talked about, is that
people gathered for a picnic.
- They came out to watch from Washington.
They brought the carriages out,
set up on a little ridge that let
them look down over the battle.
- So that kind of gives you a sense
that people of the time, first of all,
didn't think this would-- this is going
to scale to the size that it
did or last as long as it did,
but also not understand the
seriousness of the situation.
- They're clueless about what's actually
going on. To even think that you should go
observe a battle like that
is ridiculous, but they did.
And there was a strong belief,
and Lincoln was part of
this at the beginning, that there's probably
gonna be one battle. It's not gonna last.
He asked for 90-day volunteers to suppress
the rebellion right after Fort Sumter.
William Tecumseh Sherman reacted to that
by saying that you might as well try to
put out a fire with a squirt gun. I mean,
it's ridiculous. They're not thinking
about what this war could easily
be. Take years, take hundreds of
thousands of men maybe, not one battle.
- When did it, the dark cloud, the
reality of the war, come in?
- Well, First Bull Run and
Star or Manassas, th- each
side, many battles have two names, one
that the United States soldiers used
and one... And usually the Confederates
would pick the nearest town,
and the United States often picked
terrain features, so you get Bull
Run, which is a creek or stream. That's
what the Union soldiers called it.
Manassas is what the Confederates
called it. Antietam,
a creek in Maryland, is what the Union.
Sharpsburg is what Confederates called
it. Anyway, there are several of those.
That brought a little sense
of reality to people in the
United States especially. They'd expected it to
be over, and it didn't go the way they thought
it would go, and so it's gonna
take more men. The summer of
'61 was spent, hundreds of thousands of
men went into uniform in the summer of
'61. The whole supply situation
became more evidently imperative,
but not much happened
in the, for the rest of the war. There's a pretty
big battle called the Battle of Wilson's Creek
that takes place in Missouri, but
the rest of 1861 doesn't have... The
real fighting begins in the spring of '62,
and what really brought home
in a way that no one had
imagined what could be in store was one
battle in the East and one battle in the
West. The one in the West is Shiloh,
which happened in early April.
U.S. Grant on the, on the United
States side and a General Albert
Sidney Johnston on the Confederate
side. But at Shiloh in two days,
there were upwards of 25,000
casualties, and that's more,
more battle casualties than U.S.
forces had suffered in every
war combined down to that
point happened in two days.
Two and a half months after
that—George B. McClellan's army
engaged with Lee's army in what came to be
called the Seven Days Battles at Richmond,
36,000 casualties. So
those two together just
showed that this was gonna be
on a totally different scale,
and it was gonna involve
sacrifices and allocation of
resources that no one had imagined before.
- Since you mentioned Missouri, you've talked
about how that was the most brutal guerrilla
warfare of the conflict.
And maybe can you speak to what do you mean
by guerrilla warfare? What kind of war
was that? And then contrast
with the structure,
the dynamics of battles
elsewhere in the war.
- Yes. Guerrilla war is more of what
I think most Americans can sort of
imagine what guerrilla war is.
It involves much, much smaller
numbers of actors, obviously, on
both sides. Guerrilla bands might have
a few dozen members. They might have
a few hundred at different times.
There are no real battles,
battles between guerrillas.
There is a lot of
bushwhacking, which is what they called it,
ambushing people, terrorizing civilians,
killing livestock, killing some
civilians, killing prisoners after you've
captured them, hanging some
people. There are a few semi-large
scale ones. There's a Confederate
guerrilla named Quantrill led a raid
against Lawrence, Kansas, where
they burned parts of the town,
executed more than 150 men in the
town, and terrorized the place.
That is going on in the... There's a
relationship in many places between
elevation and guerrilla activity. The
more mountainous or hilly, the more likely
there'll be guerrillas operating. They operate
in the mountains, East Tennessee, western
North Carolina, southwestern Virginia,
Central... There's even some activity
in parts of Texas, but Missouri and
Kentucky have the worst guerrilla warfare.
It's present through the whole war,
probably involves maybe
50,000 men out of the
3 million who were in
action during the war,
and was very nasty, no rules. One
reason that rules of war were codified
was because Henry Halleck, who was a
Union general in Missouri, was dealing
with this guerrilla activity and he said, "We need
to get some rules about who's a civilian, who's
not a civilian. How do you deal with
this kind of situation and that
kind of situation?"
- What should we take away from the
fact that most of the fighting
had the rules of war behind it? So
it was more structured, it was-
- I think what we take away from that
supports my argument that
this is a war between two
mid-19th century nation states that
have a sense of how you fight a
war. You fight a war with
national armies who are led by
professional soldiers and who understand
that there are limits to what you
do in a war, and all the war, the
war's limits expand as it goes on,
but it doesn't reach the point where you
have indiscriminate killing of civilians and
so forth. You just don't... I mean, there's an
argument about whether it's a total war or not.
It all depends on how
you define total war.
- As you've mentioned, in terms of
how encompassing it was, as total a
war as it gets because the, the entirety
of the society was involved in it.
- When there's wide-scale targeting
of the economic infrastructure
of your opponent that can be used to support
the war effort, which is what you get
increasingly as the war goes on and
officially when Grant is in charge as
general-in-chief, then certainly that's
a total... If you're the farmer who
experiences an army coming
by and they, they take
all, take or kill all your livestock
and destroy your crops, and that's,
that's pretty much like a total
war, even if they don't kill you.
- So the war escalates.
- Yes, the war does escalate.
'62, it takes a quantum leap.
In the spring and early summer of 1862,
the signals are clear this is something
that we had not counted on before.
And the armies are much, they're gonna be much
bigger. The Army of the Potomac's more than
100,000 men. There's never been an army
like that in US history, nothing like that.
- What do we understand from the
diaries of soldiers coming,
For the first time face to face with
this scale of war? We're talking
about a year. They've been volunteering
for a year, like you mentioned,
you know, in the summer, in the
spring and the summer of '62.
- There's so many themes in soldier
letters, and it's an incredible gift
to people such as myself who
study this, is that almost, that
a very large majority of the men
on both sides were literate.
And so we have this mass of testimony.
And they, and they, they sent
millions of letters from the armies
home and, and back to the armies, the,
the on both sides. So we have this,
this trove of first-hand
evidence and diaries too, many,
many, many, many, many diaries.
But so you can see in real
time how attitudes are changing,
hardening. You can see the
hardening process in soldiers who they don't
have any idea what being a soldier is,
then they do, and they don't like lots of things
about it. They don't... They talk a lot about food,
talk a lot about clothing, talk
a lot about officers they don't
like. They don't talk, what
one thing, it's really
fascinating, the thing they
don't try to do is explain to
people behind the lines exactly what
it's like to be in a battle because they
understand the people back home won't
understand what they're talking about. And so
they'll say things like, "It was awful,"
and, "Words just can't convey what
it was," and then maybe tell
more about their individual
experience. But there's a real sense
that what a veteran knows about
being in the military and what the
people back home will understand are two different
things, and you just can't explain it to them.
- And so that takes us into the
fall of the Battle of Antietam.
Can you walk me through what happened
at the battle and why it mattered?
- George B. McClellan, whom I've already
referred to dismissively a couple of times-
He was-
... he was in charge of the Army of the
Potomac by this point. He'd been general
in chief for a brief time and
commanding the Army of the Potomac.
And he finally approached Richmond.
He got within, literally within
five miles of Richmond. He was opposing
an officer named Joseph E. Johnston,
who just, his first thought every day was,
"What a great day to retreat. Where could I go?
I could go that way, or I could go that way."
He and McClellan were a match made in heaven.
McClellan didn't wanna go anywhere,
and Johnston only wanted to
retreat. Anyway, they finally
ended up at Richmond.
Johnston got wounded, got hit
by a shell fragment outside
Richmond in the Battle of Seven Pines,
and he's replaced by Robert E. Lee.
And McClellan, in his usual perceptive
way, observed that this was great because
he knew that Lee was too timid to ever be
an effective presence on the battlefield.
So he read him just exactly the way-
... that McClellan would. He
ends up fighting Lee, and he,
in the Seven Days' Battles, McClellan is
pushed away from Richmond. He shouldn't have
been, but he was. That was
considered a great victory.
Lee's reputation goes
up after that. Then Lee
follows that up with the campaign
of Second Bull Run, which
reorients the war from
Richmond to Manassas,
the old First Manassas battlefield in
northern Virginia. Stonewall Jackson plays
a key role in it. He wins the Battle
of Second Bull Run in late August
1862, and then invades the loyal
states for the first time. He crosses
into Maryland in early September
with an army that is broken
down in terms of supply.
He has tremendous straggling problems
and desertion problems, Lee did,
in ... He moved across the army
with about 50,000 men. When they
finally came to battle at
Antietam, which is in western
Maryland, he only had about 35,000
soldiers on the field. McClellan had
about 80,000 on the other side.
And McClellan had captured a copy
of Lee's entire orders for the
whole campaign, Special Orders
Number 191. They had gone
through an old Confederate camp- ...
and found a copy of Lee's orders.
And still McClellan didn't move quickly.
I won't bash McClellan. They fight.
The bloodiest single day in US
history is Antietam, the battle of
23,000 casualties in one
day there. Very close
thing. Lee hangs on by
just the narrowest margin,
sits on the battlefield for another whole day,
which he shouldn't have done. He was being way too
bold there, and then retreated,
got back across the Potomac River.
Confederates looked at this whole thing
as a drama in three acts:
save Richmond, reorient the
war to northern Virginia, cross into
the United States, and they saw it as
a success. Richmond's
no longer threatened.
Lee's reputation has gone way up. McClellan
has frustrated Lincoln immeasurably,
and as a result, Lincoln removes
McClellan from command. He waits
till the day after the elections in
November 'cause McClellan's popular among
Democrats, and Lincoln is an adept
politician. He fires him the day
after the elections and replaces him
with a guy named Ambrose Burnside.
- So what can you say about what makes a great
general and what makes a poor general in
all of this?
- Well, McClellan is a very smart guy,
and he was on Winfield
Scott's staff in Mexico, as
was Lee, which is a sign that
you're a pretty bright officer.
He built the Army of the Potomac. He did
a brilliant job building the Army of the
Potomac. The troops loved him. There
was never a bond with any other
commander the way they had with
McClellan. But what he couldn't
do when the moment came.
When the moment came, he
couldn't risk things. He was risk-averse.
He had a chance to capture Richmond
against Lee. He should have, and
he didn't. He withdrew. He had a
chance ... You almost never had a chance
to destroy another army in the Civil War.
He had a chance to destroy Lee's
army at Antietam, and he didn't. He
pulled back. He didn't even
use 20,000 of his men. They
never fired their muskets at Antietam.
If you're in Lee's army, you're gonna
fire your musket. If you're in McClellan's
army, maybe, maybe not. He didn't
at Antietam. He let Lee get away.
It frustrated Lincoln immensely,
and Lincoln finally fired him
because of that. It was a flaw. He
lacked what they would've called in
the mid-19th century the moral courage
to risk everything. Grant had it. Lee
had it. McClellan didn't have it.
- One of the components of a great general
is the willingness to risk it all,
Obviously with, with good
advice, with intelligence, but--
- Which he had.
- ... risk failure.
- The whole war changed in this arc
between the Seven Days and Antietam,
and it changed in this
way. McClellan's defeat at
the Seven Days. This is
in late June and the, and
early July '62, convinced both Congress
and Lincoln that slavery was gonna
have to be put on the table. The
war's gonna be moral and con-- McClellan
could've won the war with slavery intact.
He didn't, so Congress passed the
Second Confiscation Act in late
July, which I mentioned earlier,
which strikes at slavery.
And then Lincoln decided, he
told his cabinet toward the end
of July that he was gonna issue
a proclamation of emancipation,
and he was persuaded that he couldn't just do
it then in the wake of a defeat. He should
wait until he had a victory. He got
another defeat at Second Bull Run.
He finally got a victory at Antietam
because Lee retreated, and then that's
when he announced the preliminary
proclamation. The key battle here isn't
Antietam. The key battle is the Seven
Days and McClellan's defeat that
persuades Lincoln to do this.
Antietam gives him the occasion to do
it, and he issued his
preliminary proclamation
five days after the battle
on September 22nd, 1862.
- Can you elaborate why it became
obvious that the slavery has to be
on the table as, as the motivation,
as the driving motivation-
... for the war at that time?
- Because people believed the...
And they were right. The war was
almost over at the end of
May 1862. It had been a
catastrophe for the Confederacy
in the Western Theater.
They had lost New Orleans. New Orleans
was surrender- the biggest city in the
Confederacy by far, 160,000
people, four times bigger than the
next biggest con- the most
important port. The key to the
Mississippi River Valley as a, as
an economic artery. If you don't
control New Orleans, the
Mississippi isn't an economic river
for you. New Orleans was gone in April.
Nashville was gone, the key
city and capital of Tennessee.
Memphis was gone in June. The
whole state of Tennessee, except
the mountainous East Tennessee, was
basically not a Confederate state anymore by
May 1862.
There was a Union army of 100,000 in
northern Mississippi by the end of May.
Catastrophic. And George B.
McClellan's army was in five miles of
the national capital in Richmond.
I don't think the Confederacy could
have absorbed the loss of Richmond at
that point. I think it would've
been over, and emancipation
was not on the table yet in an official
way. The fact that Richmond didn't fall
convinced people in the North that
the war was gonna have to last a lot
longer. The Confederates were gonna be
harder to beat, convinced Europe of the same
thing. By Europe, I mean France
and England. That's what
mattered. And so they decided that
they were gonna have to take more
extreme measures, and then the key,
more extreme measure is strike at
slavery. Strike at it as
a war measure directly.
- And as a war measure, it
what? Attacks at the economic
infrastructure of the Confederacy.
- It attacks the, the economic infrastructure
that enables the Confederacy
to maintain the largest
possible army in the war.
- So this is not about the, the ethics,
the morality of slavery. It's the-
- It is for the abolitionists who see it, and
Frederick Douglass realized that this is
good. The abolitionists
realized early on, even in
1861, some of them, Charles
Sumner, for example, saw
the Union defeat at First Bull
Run. "Yes, it's bad that we
lost, but the longer the war
goes, the more likely that
we can get slavery on the table, get
emancipation on the table." Frederick Douglass
believed the same thing.
A longer war made that more
likely, and McClellan handed them
that gift by not being as aggressive as
he should've been at Richmond in 1862.
- But we should say, and correct me if
I'm wrong, that only a tiny minority
of Americans were
abolitionists at that time.
- We'll never know exactly. I would
say if you... I think if you guessed
3% were- I mean, really
abolitionists, destroy
it now, destroy it completely,
no compensation for rebel owners
or any owners, kill it in Kentucky,
kill it in Missouri, kill it in
Maryland. Yes, I think 3%
would be about the ballpark.
- So of course, now we
venerate those folks, and
we mythologize them, and so
they become bigger in our
minds. But we should remember
that they're a tiny percentage.
- They're a tiny percentage, and there are
other factors that are pushing forward the
process that leads to the 13th Amendment.
It's not just people who hate slavery so
much that they'll do anything to kill it.
The... in fact, most of them
aren't. That's not what they are.
We wish they were, but they're not.
And Lincoln is in a tough position.
Lincoln hates slavery personally, but
he's president trying to win a war,
and he can't win the war with just Republicans.
He has to try to keep Democrats on
board, so he has to... I mean, and
the Constitution protects slavery.
In Kentucky and Missouri and Maryland
and Delaware. They're still in the
nation. The Constitution still
applies. Congress, by the time, by
the end of June, had already gotten rid of
slavery in the only two places where it
could. And that is in the federal
territories and the District of Columbia.
No compensation in the territories, but
there were hardly any enslaved people there,
and there was some compensation
in the District of Columbia.
- You said that Lincoln hates slavery.
Can we just take that tangent and
from a perspective of some,
there's a hypocrisy there
in pushing for a policy of colonization.
- Colonization. Yes,
colonization. In the summer of
1862, Lincoln met with a group of
Black leaders and tried to convince
them to support colonization,
which colonization
meant if you freed enslaved people, then
they would go somewhere else. They'd
go out of the United States. It's
why Liberia exists. And Lincoln,
that is probably the least
attractive element of his total
thinking on... He genuinely didn't
believe that white people would
ever accept Black people as equals. He told
the leaders that when he met with them, and he
said, "You wouldn't want it that way. I
wouldn't either. It's the way it is. It's
a reality."
- Do we know he believed that, or
is this a pragmatic politician
understanding the lay of the land?
- I think for someone who was
born in Kentucky and reared in
Southern Indiana and Southern
Illinois, he was never around
anything but a level of intensity
on race that he probably
didn't ever see, wasn't ever around
white people who he could see
accepting Black people as fully
equal. That's- ... I do believe that.
- And still, it is a country
that where the words
"All men are created
equal" is on the page.
- They're right there on the page,
waiting for that to be made good
on. Yes, that's correct. Well, it's true.
And Lincoln-- I mean, Lincoln
also was capable of growth.
- Well, he seemed to have evolved
quite a lot in the years of the war.
- He did. No, he did. He did.
- And it's very, very possible were he not
assassinated, he would've arrived
at a very different worldview.
- We'll never know, but we
do know that he was a lot
smarter and a lot more adaptable
and a lot more politically
adept than Andrew Johnson, and
so it certainly would've looked
different. Well, it's true.
- No, I just-
- Yes, it is true.
- ... I think I vaguely remember
you saying somewhere that Andrew
Johnson is the second worst
president in America's history.
- Yeah, he's right. He has... the
glory of being above James Buchanan.
I said that a few years ago, yes.
- I think you said something about Buchanan.
is... There's like a basement, there's
like a basement below basement. I think-
- Sub-basement. He's in the sub-basement.
- ... He's in the sub-basement. And this I
put that in the category of the slime, uh-
... poetic commentary. Uh-
- He's in a little corner of the sub-basement
all by himself with one candle.
- So can we take that tiny tangent of
why they were terrible pr- uh, tangent
on a tangent, why was Andrew Johnson such a
terrible president, and Buchanan as well?
- I think he was a terrible
president because he was,
he was extremely prejudiced.
He had all kinds of grievances
stacked up. He had the poor white
man's grievance from being in a
slavehold. He hates... His slaveholders were
part of his enemies when he was growing up,
then he embraced them after the war.
He was... He couldn't get beyond his most
profound lifelong prejudices. He was not
malleable in any way. He thought what he
thought, and that's what he was always
gonna think. And he just was not the
right be- person to be in place.
- Well, why is Buchanan the worst
president- ... in America's history?
- If you had a dictionary that had the word
hack in it, it should have a picture of
James Buchanan by it. He was
an absolute political hack-
... who made his way up by staying alive
and doing everything that you should
do as a party hack as you went
along. And then, oh, I ended up as
president in 1856 because there's
a... The person I'm running
against is from a party, this is the first
time they're running a candidate. His
way of dealing with the secession crisis
was basically hiding under his desk and
hoping the roof didn't fall in before he
got out of Washington. He's just, he's just
horrible.
- I think from that I get a sense that what
you admire in a leader and a president
is a, is a kind of backbone, uh-
... to be able to, again, take
risks and to stand behind
political savvy, yes, but also
a backbone behind that savvy.
- Yes, and to actually change a
position if you're persuaded-
... by both events and good counsel that
you had the wrong position before. Go
ahead and do that.
- So some kind of balance of, of a
backbone behind principles and
malleability based on the information,
knowledge, and wisdom that you gain-
... versus for convenience or out of fear.
- There's an apocryphal story about Lincoln
that I think gets at his willingness to
row against the tide if he needed to. He's... They're
discussing something in a cabinet meeting, and he
says, "Well, let's, let's vote. Let me get
your sense." And they went around the table,
and every cabinet member
voted no. And, and
Lincoln said, "Well, that's
six nos and one yes. Mine,
the ayes have it." I mean, he's...
So he listened to them, and in that
case, he's willing to do something
that's unpopular and knows that he's
gonna get... But he'll do it because... And
that's, that's a quality not everybody has
either.
- Who's the greatest president
in the history of the United-
- In my view?
In my view, it's neck and neck with Washington
and Lincoln. Without Washington, there's no
United States, so it's sort
of hard to go against him.
He set all kinds of precedents
that were really important.
- Just giving away power.
- Twice. He did it twice. The Europeans
couldn't wrap their minds around that. He
gave it away after the revolution.
In other words, his message
is, "I'm not Caesar. I'm
not Cromwell. I'm not
Napoleon." There hadn't been a Napoleon
yet, but anyway, he wasn't one.
"I had power, and I gave it back." And then he
stepped down. He would've been president for
life if he wanted to be. He did two terms.
That's enough. Let somebody else do it.
Who does that? But he embodies the notion
of what... This is what a citizen soldier
does. He comes forward at
a time of crisis, he does
his duty, and when the crisis
is over, he is Cincinnatus.
He goes back to his farm when
this is over with, because the
point is, he'd done what
republic... small R republican
virtue dictated, and then he went back.
And, and that image was
invoked over and over and
over again. The small R repub- This has
nothing to do with the Republican Party.
Small R republican virtue
of disinterested service
to your republic. It's... And
Washington embodied that.
He's crucial. What's always been
fascinating to me, Lex, is you have
this guy, he's surrounded
by this freakishly
talented group of people in
this little nation. You have
Madison and Hamilton and Jefferson
and Franklin, all these people
who are probably smarter than Washington.
They've certainly read more Greek and
Latin than Washington, and yet nobody's
concerned about who the man is.
It's Washington. He's
the guy. We're smarter.
It's like what Sherman
said about Grant one time.
Sherman's smarter than Grant, probably.
Sherman said, "I know more about strategy than
Grant. I know more about tactics. I know
more about supply. I know more about
everything than U.S. Grant does.
But where he beats me and where
he beats the world is he don't give
a damn what the enemy is doing
out of his sight, and that scares me like
hell." In other words, Grant could just
let the background noise go
away, focus on his thing, and
do what he was gonna do, and
Sherman couldn't do that. Grant
liberated Sherman to become a great
general because he had Grant over him
taking responsibility.
It's really fascinating. And Washington,
whatever faults he had, he could take
responsibility, and was
aware that he was setting
precedents as the first president
of this new republic almost
every time he did something. It's a
precedent. What did Washington do?
Well, he gave up his uniform, and
then he gave up the presidency
- Yeah, just from studying history,
understanding how difficult it
is to give away power in the way that
Washington did, I have to put him as the number
one.
- Yeah, because without him,
the rest doesn't happen.
I mean, that's my bottom line on it, and I really
do believe that. Without him, the rest doesn't
happen. I don't know what... If they hadn't
had Washington to persuade people that
a stronger central government might be
possible because Washington's gonna
be president, who else would they
agree could be trusted? There's
Washington, and then
there's everybody else.
- And I think America's a truly
positive force in human history.
So the fact that whatever ideas that
were created at that time, and that
Washington was the foundation of
that, is a great gift to humanity.
- Lucky to have him, lucky to have Lincoln.
We've been lucky in our leaders, Indy.
We're lucky to have FDR in World War
II. I mean, we've been lucky to have-
... people at moments of real crisis.
- But we need the basement, too. We
need, we need the full variety.
- Well, we've got them.
And you never know when we might need
a new sub-basement. So it's just
complicated and an ongoing story.
- Man, it is a beautiful theater,
a beautiful drama, and
I, like you, have faith in the
resilience of the people to
deal with the full mess of it.
Quick bathroom break if it's okay.
- Yeah.
- I wanted to mention to you just as
a plug, but also as a big thank you
that I don't know how many
hours, it must be maybe over 50
hours I've enjoyed listening to your Great
Courses. So you have two on the American
Civil War and on Robert E. Lee.
- Right.
- And so I just wanted to mention this
thing that I've been using. It's called
Plaud. So what I do is
I run along the river,
and then I'll use this Plaud thing
where you just press the button,
and then you leave a note, like what
I'm saying now is being recorded.
- Right.
- And then it's transcribed. Those
notes are then transferred.
- God, technology. Geez.
- Yeah, this thing is great. So it's great for just...
It's been running this whole time, too, so it's
transcribing automatically.
It's using AI to transcribe-
- Oh, so it's doing every word,
everything that we say?
- Yeah. You know, transcribing it into text.
- Right. Right.
- And then it can summarize it for you,
and then I organize and study the notes
afterwards. This thing is great. Highly
recommend it. It's called Plaud.
- Plaud.
- Plaud. It's a clip.
- I used to run around Town Lake or what
was, I guess it's Lady Bird Johnson
Lake now. Is that what they call it?
We used to run six miles a day at noon
for years when I worked at the LBJ Library.
We had a little group of us who went.
- Just run?
- Just ran. We'd do it in... We
would do six miles in 38 minutes.
- It's actually a really hard problem
to solve, of how to not take memory.
I'm just really happy this exists. Okay.
'Cause my smartphone was being a pain
in the ass, like writing it down. It's been,
it's been a hard problem for me to solve.
You listen to audiobooks
or no? Or you just read?
- All the time on my w-
I walk... I don't run anymore, but I
walk six or seven miles a day, and
I listen to Audible all the time.
That's what I do. I love Audible.
- Well, just out of curiosity,
just take that tangent.
Do you listen to, like, history books?
Like what... Or do you wanna escape?
- I listen to a mixture. I
listen to some history books,
but I also listen to
some mysteries and some-
- So fiction is also-
- Oh, fiction, oh yeah. Yeah, and
some books that I think I should
listen to and haven't ever gotten around
to reading. I did Moby Dick that way.
- Mm-hmm. So the classics also?
- Oh, yeah. But I've never
read War and Peace, and I
don't think I ever will. I think... I
would've done it by now if I was going to.
- We're making a statement today. I like a
person who's not, not always,
but I like short books.
- I do too. I write short
books. A lot of long books
would make good short books, and a lot of
short books would make good essays, I think.
- Yeah, can you... Ugh, I'm sorry to be taking
so many tangents 'cause you've written so many
excellent books. How much of it is editing?
Like how-- or what does it take to
write a good history
book? What's the process?
- Well, for me, it's having
either a question that you wanna
answer or having some strain in the
literature that you think is wrong,
and you need to... For me, the
Union War was trying to rescue something
that I thought people just don't understand
anymore, is what union meant to
that generation. It makes more
sense... A war fought to
end slavery makes sense to
us now. That's, of course, it's a
monstrous institution, fight a war...
but that's not what it was about
for most of the people. And to
get at what it was about is a harder
pull, and explaining what union then
meant to an era where it doesn't
mean anything. I mean, union as they
understood it does-- it's not in
our vocabulary anymore. It has
to do with labor relations now. But to say,
"What is-- but what does the concept of
union mean?" Get crickets.
- Is it basically a strong sense of nation?
So, like, what... Can we just kinda
pull that apart? So there's
different states, and
uh, Americans have always had a sense
of, like, "I'm from this state" pride--
- Absolutely.
- ... being from the state.
- You have different loyalties.
You have a state pride and
and a and maybe even a regional
pride. I think... I wrote
a little book where I talked about Robert
E. Lee in that regard as part of it, where
he has a sense of loyalty to
the nation, to the state, to
the slaveholding South,
and so forth. But union,
I mean, it's composed of individual
states which engender loyalties
among the people who live in them,
but the parts make a greater whole,
and that's what the union is,
and you have to have the whole--
To get all the benefits.
Because... And that is what people
thought then, and they tied it to the
revolution, of course, and tied it to
earlier sacrifice, and tie- They had an eye
on what's going on in Europe. I
mean, the Western world is, was
their world. They didn't care that much about the
rest of the world. But the Western world, what's
going on there, and I think they believed
things were going the wrong way in much of
Europe, that the revolu-- the all the
revolutionary fervor of the 1840s
had seemed to run into a cliff of o-
oligarchy and aristocracy
and monarchy, and,
and they saw the US as a bulwark
against that for small D democracy.
- I think having a faith in nation
is a beautiful thing. It's a
narrative that unites a people.
And I think that in itself has power.
It's not ... You can make an economic
argument, you can make a freedom
argument, all these arguments you can
make, but I think what makes
a nation is a bunch of
people believing in a narrative. It's
like what makes a great company. There's
a mission. The power of humans
when you together believe in a
thing is, is remarkable. And so that
belief in itself is really powerful.
- That clearly was there,
Among many, many, many, many. Not everybody,
of course, but it was widespread.
And Lincoln articulated it- ...
perfectly, and he did it again and again,
talking about give, give the ...
You wanna give a person a chance to
rise, a person... And talking
about the last best hope of
Earth, and talking... I mean, he
got it, and he distilled it, and he
conveyed it. And
it's not as if he's telling people
things they don't already know, but he's
reaffirming things in ways that
are eloquent and memorable.
- Quick ten-second thank you to our sponsors.
Check them out in the description. It
really is the best way to
support this podcast. Go to
lexfridman.com/sponsors. And now, dear
friends, back to the conversation.
All right. So we were talking about, uh-
- Where are we?
- ... Antietam.
- Okay.
- And how that was, uh, the
moment when The Union realized-
- Preliminary Proclamation
- ... Preliminary Proclamation, where it's
like, okay, slavery has to be a thing
as a central part- ... of the Civil War.
And so where does that take us? Also
very bloody battle. The generals, McClellan,
the end of the McClellan chapter,
and that takes us to Fredericksburg.
So what happened at Fredericksburg?
- Fredericksburg was a
... It's another victory for Lee. It's an
easy victory for Lee. He has a very strong
position on high ground across the
Rappahannock River from the Union
forces, who are opposite Fredericksburg.
His opponent is a guy named Ambrose
Everett Burnside, who's a very
affable guy, kind of a nice guy, who
gave us the word sideburns. He
wore his whiskers that came
down and came up and made, and-
- Nice
- ... it wasn't a beard, and they
were called burnsides at the time.
The burnside cut, which was
transposed into sideburns.
Everybody liked him. He just wasn't
very bright in some ways. He's a
politician after the war, so he
went into the right field, but His idea at
Fredericksburg- ... was to, in the end,
it wasn't his original plan, but he ended up
launching frontal assaults one brigade at a
time against very strongly entrenched
Confederates, and it was a butchery
for ... And another horrible defeat
for the Army of the Potomac.
Lincoln was really cast
down by it, and it just
seemed that in this Eastern theater, he
could not get any good news. He's getting
good news from the West. He's not
getting any good news here, and he has
this revolving door of commanders.
Burnside tried another
march in late January
1863. He was gonna get around Lee's
flank, but he had horrible weather.
His army literally got stuck
in the mud. Then it was
lampooned as the Mud March,
and he removed him from
command. So now he has another commander
in the Army of the Potomac. So you've had
McClellan and Burnside, and
now a guy named Joseph Hooker.
You have no continuity at the top in that
army. You have complete continuity at
the top in the Army of Northern Virginia, which
is a huge advantage to the Army of Northern
Virginia.
- So this is where the, the famous
words of Robert E. Lee were...
He was watching the slaughter.
He said that "It is well that war is so
terrible, or we should grow too fond of it."
What did he mean by that?
- He was getting... I mean, he was
watching his soldiers butcher
Union soldiers and, I guess,
kind of enjoying it. Uh,
he's in a really strong position with
really guard artillery supporting his
infantry, and the Union troops are
just attacking them and not having
any success. And so there he is. He's up
there with James Longstreet and other
people and watching it. And he, unlike
McClellan, was willing to risk,
obviously, piling up casualties in every battle.
Didn't have that many at Fredericksburg.
There were about 12 and a half thousand
US casualties at Fredericksburg and about
5,500 Confederate casualties
because they were so
well-protected in their defensive lines.
- So you are working on a
manuscript on Chancellorsville.
It's a legendary battle for many reasons.
Can you break down some of the military,
details of what made up that
battle to give us a sense of,
in general, what battles were like?
- This is often described
as Lee's most successful
battle. It's him against Joseph
Hooker. It's the last battle
that Lee and Jackson fought as a team,
Lee and Stonewall Jackson, with Stonewall
Jackson as his principal subordinate.
Hooker had replaced Burnside.
Hooker had maneuvered to get
rid of Burnside. He wanted
to be in command of the army. He, he had
made a statement that he said what the
nation needed was a dictator to make
sure it won. And Lincoln, one of
the best letters a president
ever wrote to a military
commander, Lincoln wrote to
Hooker, and he said basically,
"I know everything you're saying. You're
talking about all the things you're gonna
do." And he said that, "The only
way you get to be a dictator is if
you have victories, and I'm willing to
risk a dictatorship to get victories. And
so I know I've got you figured out,
Joe," he's saying, and he did.
Hooker made a lot of blustery talk.
He got a... He had a great start.
He built the army into what he called
the greatest army on the planet, about
135,000 men, beautifully supplied,
reorganized the medical service in it.
He, he did everything that you
should do to get an army in shape,
and then he started a campaign.
His plan, Lee was still at
Fredericksburg. He was gonna get around
Lee's left flank, come in behind
him, force Lee to either retreat to Richmond
or fight him on unfavorable ground.
Everything went well with
Hooker. He got going in late
April until the moment of truth came.
The moment of truth came on May
1st, 1863, when Lee,
instead of retreating,
left part of his army to watch one part
of Hooker's and turned around to meet
Hooker head-on near a crossroads
called Chancellorsville
a few miles west of Fredericksburg.
And as soon as the fighting
started, McClellan lost his nerve-
... pulled into a defensive
position. And the upshot was
after Lee and Jackson carried off
a very successful flank attack,
although it left Hooker still in a very
strong position, Hooker in the end
retreated, and it was another victory for
Lee in a battle he never, ever should
have won. He was outnumbered two to one,
135,000 to about 64,000.
And when the moment of truth came, Joseph
Hooker just lost his nerve. I mean, I
really do believe that. I had fun
working on this book. I wrote a
... A lot of books on campaigns are very long
and detailed. I wanted a short book that would
introduce interested readers who didn't
really know that much perhaps to ...
There's one of the maps.
- So there are different, there's different
positions, the different troops' positions.
There's Hooker.
- Yes. That is the ... The battle
played out on May 1st, 2nd, and
3rd. There's the opening
of the campaign. See the
Rappahannock River, Fredericksburg.
The armies are facing each other
there. Hooker's plan was to leave
part of his army to hold Lee's attention
and move the rest up the river,
up the Rappahannock, cross the
Rappahannock and then the Rapidan, and get
behind Lee so that Lee
would be caught in a vise.
He'd have Hooker in his rear and
the anvil of other Union troops at
Fredericksburg, and he thought that that would
force Lee to retreat toward Richmond and that he
could then harass him. They get around,
they get behind Lee. They do exactly what
Hooker wanted to do. He got to
Chancellorsville. He had more than
70,000 men at Chancellorsville,
and Lee doesn't find out till the
very end of April what's going on, and
then he decides to divide his army,
leave 10,000 men to watch 40,000
Federals at Fredericksburg, and he
and Stonewall Jackson head back
toward Chancellorsville to
meet Hooker. And they
meet on May the 1st. The
fighting starts on May the 1st.
Everybody's upbeat in the Army of the
Potomac. They've gotten around Lee's flank. They
know they're behind him. Everything seems to
go very well. Hooker said,
"This is it. We've done
it. We've done exactly what I wanted to do." And
then the fighting starts the next day on May
1st.
They march toward that place called Zoan Church.
You can see there, it's just a little bit
east of Chancellorsville. And
the fighting, they collide about
11:00 in the morning. 2:00 that
afternoon, Hooker orders a retreat.
Everybody retreats back into this wilderness.
It's a kind of cut-over, woodsy area,
that it has very few roads, and
he just hunkers down around
Chancellorsville, hands
the initiative to Lee.
The next day, Jackson
and Lee decide to send
Jackson all the way around the
right flank, and you see the
flank march there. They come,
they strike a Union corps
that's exposed, commanded by a man named
Oliver Otis Howard. Howard University
is named after him. He headed the
Freedmen's Bureau later in the war.
They strike, they crush the 11th
Corps, which has a very high
German element in it, and there's a lot of ethnic
prejudice that comes into play there by the
other soldiers. But it ends up, the
day ends up with Lee actually in worse
shape than he was before. He's got two
divisions over here under Anderson and
McLaws on the lower right.
He's not even in touch with
Jackson's corps. Jackson was
wounded that night by his own men,
carried from the field.
He'd die a few days later.
And Hooker still, although Hooker is in
between these two parts of Lee's army, he's
in an ideal position. He's still just
thinking about the defense even. Where on
the morning of May 3rd,
the two parts of Lee's army fight their
way together around the Chancellorsville-
... clearing, and Hooker then retreats
toward the north. You have this
amazing moment on May the 3rd
where Hooker, who's been stunned
by an artillery round that hit a pillar he
was leaning against at Chancellorsville-
... he had a concussion. He was
vomiting. He retreated to the rear.
And as the Union troops retreated from
that clearing near Chancellorsville,
Lee's army
had fought itself together, and Lee rode
into the middle of his troops. And there was
this amazing moment when this spontaneous
outpouring of emotion on the
part of the Confederates, that's
the moment when Lee and his men finished
this period of bonding this year that
was unmatched in the Civil War. See, there's
no way Lee should've won this battle.
There's one more day of action a
little farther to the east. But in the
end, Hooker retreats. He never should've
retreated. He was in an impregnable
position, but he did retreat.
And Lincoln was absolutely
beside himself after this. He
just couldn't ... Everybody knew what the numbers
were. The newspapers had talked about it-
... that Lee had only half as
many men as Hooker, and once
again, the Army of the Potomac, the
largest and most important army of
the Republic, has been defeated
by this smaller army. It,
Lee's sort of legend in the
North grew and in the South.
He became, by this point, he and his
army were the most important national
institution in the Confederacy. People
looked to them to see whether indep- It's
like Washington and the Continental Army
during the Revolution. If they're still in the
field, there's still a
chance for victory. This
cemented that position
for Lee, this victory at
Chancellorsville did, in the minds of
Confederates, and made him a kind of
bugaboo to people in the
North. They were just
thirsty for someone to defeat
Lee and capture Richmond.
- So this, in some sense, created
the legend of Robert E. Lee.
- It certainly helped solidi-
Yes, it did. It went a long way
toward doing it. A long way.
- So you write about, you know, the
difference between sort of reality and
memory. How does the North remember
this battle, and how does the South
remember this battle?
- It's really fascinating. The North
remembers this battle by not remembering it
very much.
- Yeah, ignoring it.
- They sort of airbrush it out of their
memory of the war. The Confederates,
in the iconography of the
Lost Cause, this ... Lee and
Jackson had their last meeting ever here
just before the fighting on May 2nd got
going, and there was a famous painting
of that done by an artist named
Julio that was then reprinted as a
lithograph that hung in innumerable homes
and offices and courthouses in
the South. It's Lee and Jackson
at high tide, kind of. Gettysburg
hasn't happened, never mind
Appomattox. These are the two greatest
Confederate soldiers at their greatest moment
of success. It became hugely
important in the Lost Cause
telling of the war. On the
Union side, they didn't
wanna talk about Joseph Hooker that much. They
had... They'd rather talk about other things.
- Yeah, it's probably one of the most humiliating
battles of the war from the Union side.
- It, I think it's, it's really,
it's just a, it's amazing that Hooker lost this.
It's just amazing. And it shows the complete
dominance of one personality over
another personality, in my view.
- So Stonewall Jackson was shot, killed.
- Shot by his own men, out trying to
reconnoiter and keep the battle going
and exploit his successes,
carried back to the rear, and he
died on May 10th, died eight days later.
- So what impact did that have
of Stonewall Jackson's death?
- Well, that had a hu-- That,
there was unbelievable mourning
across the Confederacy about that,
and even since, really interesting, even
some positive comments in the North
about how he'd been a sor-- He was misguided,
but a very religious guy and all of this
stuff, but they're quietly very, "That's
really good news for the United States that
Stonewall Jackson is dead, and really
bad news for the Confederacy."
- Outside the myth, did it actually have
a practical impact on, on the war?
- I don't think so, and the people who love Stonewall
Jackson would disagree with me, but I don't see
where he would've ... He was a very
good soldier at what he did, and Lee
used him very well, and they were
a good partnership, but I don't
see how he would've changed the
larger contours of the war. I don't.
- If we zoom out and look at Robert E. Lee,
somebody you've written about quite a bit,
studied a lot,
do you think we can use this battle to
try to understand the military genius of
the man and, in general, who he was?
- I do, and it shows both
why he was successful and
why some of the reasons he was
successful opened the way for
what should've been big defeats but
didn't. I mean, Lee's personality
was, at heart, aggressive. His first
impulse was always to take the
war to the opponent. He said, "They
outnumber us. If we just sit and wait
for them to come to us, they're gonna have
all the advantages. We need to try to
disrupt them and look for openings."
What this campaign showed was
his audacity. He divided his
army three times in the
course of this campaign in
the face of a much more powerful
opponent, which showed his audacity.
It also highlighted the overall
culture that he created in his
army, which was a culture of
risk-taking, of seeking to inflict
the greatest possible harm on your
opponent. It's the antithesis of the
culture that McClellan created in the
Army of the Potomac, which is a culture
of caution, of not taking risks,
of not doing anything until
everything is just right.
Any adult knows everything is never just right,
so if you're waiting for that, you'll never
do anything. It's the, two
cultures are absolutely
antithetical to one another,
and in the end, it shows
Lee and how what he had
accomplished, he had created an army
that was willing to absorb casualties
because it won all the time.
And they realized that that was,
they believed, making it more
likely that their whole war effort would
be successful. There are only a few
times during the war where you get a scene
like you got on May 3rd, where this whole army
sees the old man ride into their midst,
basically, and just has this ... I
think they decided at
that point, the soldiers,
that he was always gonna win, and Lee
looked at them and thought, "They can do
whatever I ask them to do." I think if you
wanna understand Gettysburg, if you wanna
understand Pickett's Charge,
you need to look back to May 3rd at
Chancellorsville, when Lee just decided that his
infantry could do anything
he wanted them to do.
- But also from the infantry
perspective, they believed in the-
- You asked me earlier about what did the
soldiers' letters say. The letters from
Lee's army, they absolutely didn't even
contemplate losing to the Army of the
Potomac. I mean, they just didn't think-
They didn't think they would lose to it
- What do you attribute that to? Is
that, does it, Robert E. Lee, to him?
- It's to Lee and the fact that they won these
victories under Lee, and that they took
these chances, and everybody tried. And they
always knew that they were outnumbered, and yet
they were still winning. The closest
the numbers had ever been at the seven
days when the armies were about the same
size, but after that, Lee is always at
a significant disadvantage in numbers,
and yet he seems to be victorious.
- So Lee's aggressiveness, like you've mentioned,
produced also staggering casualties.
- Staggering casualties. He lost
13,000 men here, and Hooker about
17,500. A much higher proportion
of Lee's army than Hooker lost in
his army. But this should've been
a disaster for Lee. Hooker
should have crushed Lee here.
Absolutely should have
crushed Lee, but he didn't.
- So there's two cases:
Lee's audacity being the
South's best hope of
winning the war, but the
other case is he was actually
bleeding the South dry.
- Yes, and historians have criticized
him for not just being on the
defensive all the time. I think Lee understood
better than many of his critics now
understand that the key was
Northern civilian opinion.
He said it more than once, "If we win
victories, it will depress their morale.
If their morale is depressed, the Democrats
will do better. If the Democrats get into
office, it's good for the Confederacy."
And he also knew that he was ... It's a
race between, "Am I gonna run out of men
before they run out of morale
... in the United States?" I think
he understood that, and I think
that was the best chance for the
Confederacy to win. And in the end, I'm
very happy to report, the
Confederacy ran out of men
before the Union ran out of
morale. And so the war went
the way it did. But I think Lee was
very perceptive in that regard. He
understood how important politically
what happened militarily was.
Much better understanding of that than a
lot of people had at the time, and better
understanding, I think, than a lot of
historians have now. And this is a horrible
time for the US because
behind the lines, people are in
ra- Democrats are unhappy with
the Emancipation Proclamation.
Just two months before this, Congress
passed the Conscription Act.
Democrats are very unhappy about that.
They're saying that Lincoln is a tyrant.
He's forcing people into a war that's
not the war they wanted to fight anyway.
Union morale is very fragile.
Morale, civilian morale at this
point, and this makes it much, much
worse. The draft riots in New York City,
the first draft numbers were pulled in
New York City in July. The draft riots
come right after Gettysburg,
but that is symptomatic of what
morale ... Desertions went up in the Army
of the Potomac after the Emancipation
Proclamation.
- So at this point, the Confederacy is
arguably very close to winning the war.
- I think this is one of the
more optimistic points
for the Confederacy, is in the late spring
and early summer of 1863. Yes, I do.
- If Robert E. Lee is correct, in that it's
all about morale, which seems like a,
a valid argument, then this feels, like,
very close to breaking the morale of the
Union.
- In the Eastern Theater, I think it is,
but in the Western Theater we have our
boy Grant ... who's operating against
Vicksburg at this point. So there are two big
campaigns kind of going on at this
time, and Vicksburg is the other one.
- Can you speak to Vicksburg? This is '63.
- Yeah, this is '63, and
Vicksburg is the last major
Confederate citadel on the Mississippi
River. They've already lost New
Orleans. They've lost ... So they've lost the
river. It's not a Confederate river anymore.
But they still have a strong point at Vicksburg,
and another one at Port Hudson in Northern
Louisiana. Grant has been operating
against Vicksburg since the winter of
'62, and he's finally, through a
series of trial and errors and
failures, he's finally found a way
that he thinks he can get to the
city. He takes great risks.
He crosses the Mississippi
River after having the Union
Navy run past all the batteries,
the artillery batteries there at Vicksburg,
and he invests the city from the
east. He's laying siege
to Vicksburg while he's
just getting his campaign to do that
started when Hooker is at Chancellorsville.
In May, he invests the city
and begins a siege that
will end just as the Battle of
Gettysburg ends, and it's, it's one
of the most impressive campaigns in
US military history, Grant's campaign
against Vicksburg. Cuts loose from
his supply lines. Nobody understands
what he's doing. Sherman doesn't get what he's
doing. Lincoln doesn't get what he's doing.
And in the end they go, "Oh, that's
what you were doing." And it worked.
And in the end, he captures Vicksburg,
which surrenders on July 4th, 1863.
And if you don't think that a
kind of religious people didn't
read divine intervention into
catching, having that happen on
July 4th, 1863, you would be incorrect.
That's the same day that Lee
retreated from Gettysburg. What?
Really? God's not putting a thumb on
the scales here? Huge victories in
the West, huge victory in the
East on the anniversary of the
Declaration of Independence.
- Well, that takes us to Gettysburg.
- Here we are at Gettysburg.
- Here we go.
- Which everybody knows, Lex, is the
turning point of the Civil War.
- Or is it? Okay.
- No.
- All right.
- Short answer.
- Well, that's first ...
Before we before we analyze
the, its role as a turning point or not-
- Yes, yes.
- ... what is Gettysburg? July 1863.
- Okay.
- Walk me through the three
days of Gettysburg.
- So Joe Hooker retreats across the
Rappahannock. Lee is frustrated because he
hasn't dealt more damage to
Hooker, and this is what he
decides to do. He decides to move
north for a second time. His
army is strengthened. He builds
it up to 75,000. This is
his army at its absolute apogee
as he gets ready to go north.
It's confident. It's
well-supplied, well-led. And so
they head north second week in June,
and here's what his goal is. He has two
main goals. He wants to take the
war out of Virginia so that the
agricultural sector isn't subject
to the presence of the army, so to
let agriculture recover a little, and
he wants to provision his army off
the rich Cumberland Valley in
Pennsylvania, siphon fodder and
food and animals while he's
north of the Potomac, and he
wants to stay up there for a long time to keep
the war out of Virginia. He doesn't wanna-- He
has no... The movie Gettysburg, he
says he wants to capture Washington.
No, he doesn't wanna capture Washington.
He knows it's too strong. He
has no idea of doing that, but he knows he'll
pull the Union Army after him and simply
reorient the war, and he knows it'll
be bad politically for Lincoln-
... if he's actually operating in the
United States. So off he goes to the north.
He gets north of the river. His
cavalry under Jeb Stuart is not
doing its job because poor Jeb,
who is a very good cavalryman but
has a sort of adolescent streak
where he has to be praised all the
time, he fights a, the biggest
cavalry battle of the war near
Culpeper, Virginia, Battle of Brandy
Station on June the 9th,
and he almost loses,
and it hurts his little feelings. And so
he decides that he needs to do something
dramatic so the newspapers
will love him again.
And he decides to ride all the way around
the Army of the Potomac, which he did when
McClellan was in command. It's easier to do it
when McClellan's in command 'cause he's never
moving. He decides he'll do it again here.
And just as he gets east of
the Army of the Potomac, the
Army of the Potomac starts to move
north, and so Stuart is trapped
with... and he can't communicate with Lee. So
Lee doesn't know what's going on 'cause his
cavalry isn't doing its job. He
spreads his army across southern
Pennsylvania and then finds out
from a sort of civilian spy,
guy named Harrison, that the Army of
the Potomac is actually following him
and is much closer, and Lee at the
end of June orders his army to
concentrate near Gettysburg and not to bring
on a battle, and they concentrate. Most
of them come together.
There's a little clash on June the
30th, but on July the 1st, the
armies make contact to
the west of Gettysburg in
a meeting engagement and more troops
coming on each side. It builds into what
turns into the three-day biggest
battle of the Civil War. It's not
something Lee had planned,
And it wouldn't have happened if his cavalry
had been doing its job, but they weren't,
and so here they come and there's
a battle that goes for three days.
Lee has the-- He takes the
tactical aggressive every day. He
does the attacking. The Federals
do the defending. Lee's army's
75,000. The other army's
about 85,000, 88,000.
And famous terrain, Little Round
Top, Round Top, Devil's Den, the
Peach Orchard, all these famous places,
and it ends on the third day. Lee
comes close on the second day, a huge
victory for the Confederates on the first
day. Third day, Lee's frustrated
and he just decides to let his infantry
take care of it for him and the
result is what most people
call Pickett's Charge. Pickett
was just a part of the charge.
12 and a half thousand infantry
in a direct assault and it fails
completely and he retreats
the next day. I think you
can draw a straight line between
May the 3rd at Chancellorsville
when his infantry fought
their way together and July the 3rd
at Gettysburg. He admits it too as he
writes letters to both his wife and Jefferson
Davis saying, "I asked too much of my infantry.
No fault is on them. All
the fault is on me."
And he was right. All the fault was on
him. He and Grant are alike that way.
They accept responsibility, not like
McClellan. His first reaction is, "It's not my
fault,"
to pick a general at random who did this.
"It's not my fault. It must be somebody else's
fault." Lee took responsibility.
He expected too much from his infantry.
His subordinates had not been
doing that good a job and they lost
the biggest battle of the war.
- What was the military mistake there?
What could Robert E. Lee have done
differently?
- I think what he could have done, the most
perceptive Confederate soldier who wrote about
the war was a guy named Edward Porter
Alexander who was the most gifted artillerist.
He's in Lee's army. He
wrote after the war,
Lee won a great victory on July
1st at Gettysburg, smashed two
Union infantry corps, had a very
strong position. He should've just
hunkered down and said, "Okay,
attack me. See what you can do."
He didn't do that. He almost certainly
would've won the battle if he had done
that, but he, his, this is where
his aggressiveness gets him in
trouble. He was pushing for
a more aggressive, more
decisive outcome right then and
he ended up costing... He lost
probably 25,000 men at Gettysburg,
at least a third of his army.
More than that, he went across the
river, went across the Potomac with
52 generals in his army.
17 of them became casualties.
He lost a third of his entire
corps of generals killed, wounded, or
captured in the Gettysburg Campaign. It's a
really bloody, costly campaign
for him and he ends up retreating
back into Virginia. It comes to it, and
Lincoln is at first very happy about it.
There's another, yet another general in
command on the Union side. Hooker's gone.
A guy named George Meade
is in and Meade does what
McClellan did after Antietam. He
lets Lee get away, doesn't really
harass him, and Lincoln is beside
himself with disappointment. He
writes a letter to Meade, thanks him for
his great victory and then says,
"You've let him get away. The war is
gonna continue indefinitely,"
says Lincoln. Then he doesn't
send the letter to... He writes
it but doesn't send it to
Meade, but he gets another guy to
tell Meade what's in it, so he-
... a guy named Halleck who's the
general in chief at that point.
Lincoln certainly did not think Gettysburg
was the great turning point of the war.
He, he probably thought it should've been,
but it wasn't because Lee got away with
his army intact. And after the battle, Lee
said, "Well, you'll see." He said, "They
lost a lot too, and they're gonna be...
There's not gonna be another big battle."
He said, "They'll be as quiet as a
sucking dove- ... for six months."
And in fact, it's 10 months before
there's another big battle in-
... the Eastern Theater,
till Grant gets there.
- Yeah, so how does Grant come from the, to
change the theater from the Western Theater
into the Eastern?
- So Gettysburg's a really important
victory for the United States.
- Yeah, but it's not the turning point.
- No, and it's not as important as Vicksburg,
because Lee gets away. Grant captured an
entire rebel army at Vicksburg.
Pemberton's whole army surrendered,
and that's the second time Grant had forced
an army to surrender. He forced one at
Fort Donelson back in February of 1862.
His victory is ... There
are no equivocations about
it. It's a victory. The Mississippi
is now all controlled by the United
States Navy, but Lee got away,
so that puts a little cloud
over Gettysburg at the time.
Grant wins one more victory in the
West after this. He wins the Battle of
Chattanooga in late 1863. And that then
puts him in position for Lincoln to
decide that he not only should be in charge
of everything in the West, he should be
general-in-chief, and that's what
brings Grant to the fore. And in March
'64, he's now general-in-chief
with the new rank of
lieutenant general on his ... He's
got three stars on his shoulders
now instead of two.
- And then that where does that
take us? That takes us to
'64 with the Overland Campaign. That
story plus Atlanta, Sherman's March.
- That sets up ... Grant is now planning
for how the whole war is gonna go.
And he envisions five components.
The two most important are he's
gonna move against Lee, and his
plan is lock up with Lee, inflict
the greatest possible damage on
Lee, prevent Lee from sending
reinforcements anywhere else, and if all goes
well, Richmond would fall. But he's not mainly
interested in Richmond. He's
interested in Lee's army,
which is what Lincoln has been trying
to get his generals to be interested in
the whole time. Destroy Lee's army,
and of course Richmond falls.
- So how is he thinking about the
clash with Lee? Grant versus Lee.
- Grant versus Lee is just confront him.
And they're still near Fredericksburg, where
they, on the Rappahannock River frontier,
engaged with him and
what they ended up with
was a period of six weeks
of continuous combat that
began with the Battle of the
Wilderness on May the 5th and
6th. The old pattern in the Civil
War, Lex, was you fight a battle,
one side retreats. It might be weeks,
might be months before you fight again.
What happened here is Lee and Grant fought
the Battle of the Wilderness. 12,000
Confederate casualties, 18,000
Union 30,000 casualties at the
Wilderness. They march for one day.
They start another battle, Spotsylvania
Courthouse. 12,000 More Confederate
casualties, 18,000 more Union casualties,
so now you've had 60,000
casualties in two battles with no
interval. That continues through May. Cold
Harbor, they end up near Richmond
at Cold Harbor in early June.
Grant launches frontal assaults
there. They come to nothing. His men
are, many of them are butchered.
The bottom line is that in the
six-week campaign, Grant
suffers 65,000 casualties,
which is as big as Lee's whole
army had been. Lee suffers
35,000, which is a higher percentage
of his army than Grant lost in, or
about the same percentage,
actually. But it is a kind of
continuous campaign no one had seen
before, and it shatters both armies.
It eviscerates the officer
corps in both armies.
armies. A lot of soldiers just break down.
We would talk about PTSD now probably.
They just hadn't been used to something
like this.
- And this kind of continuous warfare,
that's ... We can attribute that to Grant.
- Yes, this is ... And this is where
the Grant the Butcher image comes in.
- But also probably, as hard as it is to say,
it's an act of military genius, right?
- Well, it's ... He's doing what he wanted
to do. He's bleeding Lee's army and
at the same time pushing it back toward
Richmond, and what it ends up in
is the siege at Petersburg, Virginia, which
is just south of Richmond and controls
the communications into Richmond, and
it's a siege of actually Petersburg and
Richmond, and that is the thing that
Lee feared the most, and Grant had
put him in exactly that position.
But the perception behind the lines in
the United States is endless casualties.
Who's winning? We can't even tell who's
winning. We have these casualties,
and so Union morale drops
to its lowest point of the entire
war in July and August 1864. Because
while this is going on,
Sherman is moving against
Atlanta, and he is taking
his time, not fighting these
big battles, but he's not capturing Atlanta
either. The whole summer goes by. Atlanta
hasn't fallen. Richmond hasn't fallen.
There's an election coming up in the fall in
the United States, and Lincoln
decides ... The morale
gets so bad he calls his
cabinet together in late August
and makes them sign what's been called
the Blind Memorandum, and what the
memorandum said is, "We're
not gonna be reelected,
and we're gonna have to win the war before the Democrats
come in, because we know they won't win the war."
Lincoln did not think they would win.
That's in August. And so I think
that United States civilian morale,
the lowest point of the war for the
United States is in July
and August 1864. And
if we'd been able to stick our microphones
in people's faces and said, "Well, but what
about Gettysburg? That was the turning point
of the war," they would've said, "What are you
talking about?" "That was a year ago.
This is now, and we're not winning, and
it's not worth it, and we're
just about ready." McClellan,
incidentally, was the Democratic nominee for
president that year, so he's running against
Lincoln.
- So first of all, if Lincoln
didn't win, do you think-
- Well, we know it would've been good for the
Confederates if Lincoln didn't win, but just, uh ...
McClellan still ... It's interesting.
McClellan was running kind of
against the Democratic platform. What
the Democratic platform called for
was basically negotiations,
an armistice and then
negotiations. And many people
believed if they ever stop fighting,
they're not gonna start fighting again.
And so some negotiated end to the war
that might even yield a confederacy.
McClellan, to his credit, and I hate to
give him credit, at least said that he
wasn't up for that. He said, "We need to win
the war, and then we'll have negotiations."
But what's clear is... And it would've been,
would've been the end of emancipation.
The, 'cause emancipation, what became the
13th Amendment had passed through the
Senate in April of '64, but
the House voted against it.
That doesn't, isn't gonna
happen till early '65.
- How close was it that Lincoln won/lost?
- Well, Lincoln won. Grant didn't
reelect Lincoln, 'cause he,
Grant against Lee would not reelect Lincoln.
But other Grants, other things that
Grant, part of his overall plan as
general-in-chief, Sherman captured Atlanta-
... in early September. And
that just changed everything.
- That was the real turning point.
- That was a huge military turning point,
and then on the heels of that, Philip
Sheridan won a series of crushing
victories in the Shenandoah Valley,
the last of which came just before the
election, and it was Sherman, and to a
lesser degree Sheridan, that
reelected Lincoln, and not just
Lincoln, but huge Republican majorities-
... in both the House
and the Senate in 1864.
- And then the thing that broke the
back of Confederacies, Sherman's
March, 60,000 men across Georgia to
the sea, burning the infrastructure.
- Yes, as he said, "I'm gonna go across and
make Georgia howl," is how he put it.
He added a psychological twist. What Grant
envisioned his doing, and Sheridan actually
did it in the Shenandoah Valley before
Sherman did it in Georgia,
is go into an agriculturally
productive area, burn the mills, kill
the livestock, destroy the crops,
lay waste to it so that it can't
be a logistical support of the
Confederacy anymore. Sheridan did it in
the Shenandoah Valley, and then Sherman
did it in Georgia. But Sherman said,
"But I'm also going to break them
psychologically." That's what he said,
that, "I'm gonna show them that my
army can go wherever it wants to go,
whenever it wants to go, and there's nothing
Jefferson Davis can do about it." He said,
"When they decide that, they'll give up."
Didn't exactly work that way, but
that's what he-- so he marched first to
Savannah, and then the final campaign for
Sherman was up through the Carolinas. He
went up through South Carolina and into
North Carolina. And Grant laid siege to
Lee, and the siege lasted nine months,
the Siege of Petersburg in Richmond,
and finally Grant broke Lee's lines on
April 1st, 1865. Lee started a retreat.
Grant just gave him no
pause, and he ran him to
ground at Appomattox after about
a week, and Lee surrendered.
- What do we know about the
relationship between the two men?
- Grant and Lee?
- Yeah.
- Well, it's really interesting. I mean, they
basically operated in totally different
worlds. They were both
in the war with Mexico,
but they weren't with
each other in Mexico, and
they had some awkward kinda small talk
at Appomattox before they got down
to business. One said he remembered the other one,
the other one said he didn't remember him at all, and
it's so ... And
it... But Grant was very generous. He
gave 25,000 rations to Lee's army,
and to survive. Lee began the
retreat with about 60,000
men, only fewer than 30,000. His army
disintegrated in a week. He only
surrendered 28,000 at Appomattox. They
were allowed to sign a parole and go home.
- But at the peak of their,
you know Grant versus Lee,
surely they were thinking
about each other.
- They were, and I've always found this
interesting. They tended to be very
generous toward other opponents.
But Grant pretended that Lee wasn't
the best opponent he ever faced.
And Lee pretended that Grant
wasn't the best opponent he
ever faced, and it's ludicrous that
they would've actually thought that.
They clearly found out
that that wasn't true.
- It's interesting when people,
when people do that. I sometimes,
like, wonder, how is it possible,
um... There's just a million
examples of this. For example,
Hitler just completely dismissed
America as a military force.
- Oh, it's noth- they're a bunch of... Yes,
they're soft. They'll never do anything.
- I have to say, it's probably
some silly psychological
things. You s- you make up your
mind for some stupid reason.
- And then you stick to it.
- And you stick to it, and you almost,
like, against... I mean, with a lot
of great generals and leaders, you have
to be stubborn in the face of facts
sometimes-
- You do, yeah
- ... because, like, all the rational people
will tell you, you get this with Napoleon,
like, "What are you doing?" Like, the
generals, the wise, smart people around
you will say, "Don't do this."
- Grant's a perfect example of that,
Lex, at Vicksburg, where he,
he, his problem was to get his army on the same
side of the river as the Confederates, where he
could come against Vicksburg, and the
only way to do it was have the Union
Navy run p- and he said to do it. "No, don't
do it," said the Navy. "No, don't. No.
Sherman, no. Don't..." Everybody said no,
and Grant said, "Do it." And it worked.
- I mean, it has to do with the, with
I guess you've criticized once or
twice M- this guy named McClellan.
- I did, once or twice.
- That you know, you do have to take
risk. You have to take risk in order-
... to win battles.
- And I'll finish w- I can't resist
getting one more shot. Lee is often
quoted as saying that McClellan was the
most talented general he ever faced.
- Really? Hmm.
- Yeah, but that's, but what he actually
said, and the quote started with his
nephew, Fitzhugh Lee, who wrote it
in a book after the war. Lee called
McClellan the most intellectual
General he ever faced.
And I think that is not a compliment.
I think Lee is saying, "Yeah, he's
an intellectual. He thinks about this, he
thinks about ... He never does anything."
"He thinks about things." So I think it's
actually a slight, not a compliment to
McL- I really do.
Because he couldn't have possibly thought
he was the most talented one that he,
that he faced.
- I think it's a polite wink
and nod to criticize.
- It's a wink and nod.
- Uh, all right. How does the
war end? So clearly there's
the turning point with
Atlanta and Sherman's March.
- And the election of '64 is the that
drives the dagger into ... I mean,
there's no question
but that the war will be pushed to the end
because Lincoln and Grant are in charge
and they are not gonna
take their foot off the-
... the pedal. They're gonna push it.
So it's a question of time. It drags
on, still drags on another six months.
Lee surrenders on April 9th. They
lay down their arms on April 12th.
There are still tens of thousands
of Confederate soldiers under arms
in different places, but it's a
measure of how important Lee and his
army were that for everybody, virtually
on both sides, that's the end of the war.
Lee surrendered. There's no reason to push
this any farther, and other surrenders came
pretty quickly. Jefferson Davis was one
of the few people who didn't figure
that out. He thought something was still possible,
but it wasn't. That was the end of the war.
The final surrenders are over in June,
and that's it, and everybody gets
the same terms that Grant offered to
Lee. His friend Sherman tried to do
more, and they had to reign Sherman
in and say, "You can't ... No.
You're a general, not a
politician. You can't do this."
- So can we talk about April 9th? I mean,
this is a really important moment of
what Grant did in terms of how
he treated the opposing army.
- As I said earlier, he treated him
the way that he knew that Lincoln
wanted them treated and, and it may be
that Grant thought exactly the same
thing. But I think this is a
measure of how Grant was a
very ... He's a soldier who
knew his place. He has civilian
superiors. Other generals
didn't act that way. I know I'm
beating up on McClellan. He's one. Joseph
Johnston on the Confederate side is one.
They didn't really defer to their
civilian superiors. US Grant did,
and he ... And this is one of those
cases. He sent the rations. He,
he didn't know that Confederates
supplied their own horses. If you're a
Confederate cavalryman, the government
didn't buy a horse for you. You had to
supply your horse, and if a horse got
killed, you had to buy another one
or they'd make you an infantryman.
When Grant found that out, he let them
take their horses home with them. He said
they'll need them for the planting and so
forth. He did everything
in a generous way that you could
reasonably think might happen in a
situation like ... It's still an unconditional
surrender. You are surrendering.
You're going home. You're
not an army anymore. But
nobody's going to prisoner of war camps.
Nobody's doing those things. You lay your arms
down, you lay your flags down, and you lay your
ammunition down, but that's it.
- Yeah, but there's certain symbolic actions
like this that can lay the groundwork
for long-term peace.
- Yes. He didn't demand that Lee give
him his sword. He didn't do that, none
of those kinds of things
that you could have done.
- Sorry to linger on it, but there's
certain elements of humiliation that
prevent long-term peace. I
have to go back to Hitler
and what Germany experienced
at the end of World War I.
- You mean Versailles, the terms from
Versailles. No question about it.
- And some of it is economic, some of
it is geopolitics, but some of it
is just on a basic human
level humiliation.
And people are just not good
with humiliation. They remember.
- No, and they can turn that around
into something you don't want it to
be to get back national
pride. But Lincoln's
bottom line was the point is to
put the nation back together
and you ... The good way to start that is
not by imprisoning tens of thousands of
Confederate soldiers. That's not the way to
do it. Send them home. Make them accept the
terms, but then send them home
and leave them alone. The
president wanted to go after Lincoln's
death. Andrew Johnson wanted to go
after Lee, and Grant said, "I'll
resign if you do..." 'Cause I
... His term ... We extended the
terms. He's abiding by the terms.
You can't change the rules here.
- But by the way, like it should be said, is
that that's not easy to do. You have just
fought an extremely bloody
battle. There's hatred.
- There were lots of people who wanted
Davis to swing and Lee to swing. "Kill
them. Execute the rebels. They're rebels
and traitors who almost destroyed the
nation. Why are you
being so easy on them?"
Thaddeus Stevens was on board that
train. Lots of radical Republicans
were. "You need to punish them for what ... You haven't
punished them enough. You're not punished them.
Yes, you took
slavery away from them, but that's not enough.
They should be punished more for what they
did." "Confiscate their lands.
Take their wealth away from them."
- So what happened next in
terms of reconciliation?
- Well, Lincoln got assassinated
just a few days after-
... Lee's troops laid down their arms.
- Can you talk to the assassination? He was
shot five days after the surrender, right?
- Yes, he was.
- So who was Booth? Who
was John Wilkes Booth?
Why did he assassinate Lincoln,
and what impact did that have?
- Well, he was the youngest
of the most famous acting family in
the United States. Junius Brutus
Booth and Edwin Booth, his father
and older brother, were very famous
actors, and he was a very successful actor,
too, John Wilkes Booth was. He was good at
jumping around the stage,
and he was very athletic.
Um, and an ardent pro-Confederate.
- That's the more important- ... aspect
- Not ardent, not ardent enough to put on a
uniform for the Confederacy,
but ardent enough to, you know-
... argue for the Confederacy. He
claims ... I mean, not claims. He,
he heard Lincoln make a statement about
maybe Black soldiers getting the vote,
and he said that was it for him, he ...
that somebody needed to kill the tyrant.
This is very ... This is
after Lee had surrendered.
- So he was on the Union side.
- Oh, yeah. Oh, yes, he-
- But Lincoln was a tyrant in his eyes.
- Lincoln was a tyrant because of his sta-
because of his treatment of the white
South. And he had plotted earlier
to kidnap Lincoln and hold him for
ransom, and that didn't work out.
So then he got this little group of
losers around him to help. I
mean, real misfits. Their,
their plan was to kill Seward,
Andrew Johnson. They were gonna
cut off the top leadership
of the United States.
- Yep.
- Kill the vice, kill the president, kill the
vice president, kill the secretary of state.
That's what they wanted to do.
- On the Johnson side, they chickened out.
- That guy chickened out. A guy named Lewis
Powell was sent to kill Seward. Seward had
been in an accident and had
his neck in a big brace,
and he slashed at Seward, huge
scars on the side of his face,
but the knife hit the brace and didn't
kill Seward. So Seward was disfigured. His
son was wounded.
The guy who was supposed to kill Johnson
chickened out, and Booth killed Lincoln.
And there was a manhunt for Lincoln,
or for Booth. It took a while, and he
was shot in a barn rather than
captured and put on trial.
But four of the conspirators were
put on trial, including one woman, a
woman named Mary Surratt, who ran a boarding house
where some of them stayed, and they were all
hanged at Old Capitol Prison.
And the combination of th-
that hanging, they were tried
by a military commission and
hanged, but they also put on trial
and hanged the commandant of
Andersonville Prison, which was the most
infamous of the Confederate prison of war
camps. They hanged him as
well. And it seemed that
those hangings sort of took
the edge, the sort of we
need some retribution edge off
attitudes in the North. I think
those things helped offset Lincoln's
assassination in a sort of odd way
because the temperature
went down after that.
- You talk about, as maybe
a bit of an aside,
But that we Americans like to spin up
conspiracy theories about assassinations-
- We do
- ... of our presidents. So that's certainly
very true, maybe truer than most about
Lincoln's assassination.
- There was a long literature actually.
It began with a chemist named
Otto Eisenschiml many, many decades ago
that implicated Secretary of War Stanton-
... and blamed the radicals were
unhappy with Lincoln for not being
harsher on the former Confederates,
and what they wanted to do was
get him out of the way. They thought they
could manipulate Andrew Johnson if they got
Andrew Johnson in charge. So they,
then they would pose these questions. How
come no one was guarding Lincoln that night?
How come the only bridge over the Potomac
that wasn't guarded is the one that Booth
escaped across? All of these.
How come Grant didn't go to the play
with Lincoln? The Lincolns asked them.
Well, they didn't 'cause Mrs. Lincoln didn't like...
I mean, the, Mrs. Grant didn't like Mrs. Lincoln.
I mean, you, there are answers to all the
questions. But they put all these together,
added two and two and got
five, and said that it was,
it was a plot on the part of the radical
wing of the Republican Party to get rid of
Lincoln 'cause Lincoln didn't wanna
be harsh enough on the South.
- Yeah, it's difficult to
believe that dramatic,
sometimes catastrophic things happen for
seemingly... That, that like
the random, as you said, loser
- It's not satisfying. You want a more
satisfying, and that is a big conspiracy
is better. There are all these forces at
work to get rid of Lincoln, not just that
the one guy assigned to guard
Lincoln, there's no Secret Service
then, went across the
street to get a drink.
And Booth had played in that theater many
times. He knew exactly the layout. He'd
come in earlier. He'd arrange... I mean,
it, it just, that's the way it worked out.
- And I have to say, it, it's kinda interesting.
I have to be honest with my own mind
that, like, I love a good
conspiracy. My brain does.
- Every, almost everybody does.
- I think it's, what is it?
It, it's maybe depressing or
heartbreaking to know that so much
destruction can be caused by random events.
You want there to be a larger
system at play that it makes
you feel like there's a meaning
to this whole thing as opposed to the tides
of history can turn on a stupid actor
shooting one of the greatest, if not
the greatest president in the history
- That's correct. Killing
him, jumping out of
the presidential box, breaking
his leg when he hit the stage,
limping off, and getting away. Yep.
- Over 700,000 people dead, these epic
battles, all of that. Lincoln
survives all of it, and then there's
- When they had the grand review in Washington,
when Sherman's armies and the Army of
the Potomac marched over
two days, this amazing
display of the troops that had won the war,
and troops who had run the war, one of the
most common comments was, "Lincoln's
not here. Of all people who
should've been here, Lincoln should've been
here, and he doesn't get to watch this.
He's not in the presidential
box watching this."
And the soldiers talked about it too.
- It's heartbreaking, really, especially
I would've loved to see his evolution
as a leader, as a human being, and the
words he may have, he may have found
to direct us as a country, you know,
in the, in the Reconstruction.
- Yep. Would've been different.
We can't tell how different.
But it would've been different, and I
think it would've worked more smoothly.
- What was Reconstruction? How rocky was it?
- The white South liked to talk about the
occupation of the South and how they were
under the boot heel. There was
never an occupation of the former
Confederacy 'cause there never were
enough troops available to do it. The
most that were ever in
the former Confederacy
Which is three quarters of a
million square miles in size, was
30,000 men, and that was
for a very short period. By
1870, there were only about
10,000 men left. And the reason
there wasn't an occupation is because
the Northern population wasn't
willing to either pay for it
or keep men in uniform long
enough to make the White South do something
that they didn't really care about, which was
give full equal rights
to formerly enslaved Black people. The
White North just wasn't, they weren't
willing to do that. They were willing,
largely because of Andrew
Johnson's intransigence
in the summer of 1865 when he started to
act like the South hadn't even quite lost,
they were willing to push far enough
to get the 14th Amendment and the
15th Amendment, and that to me is sort
of miraculous considering what the
attitudes among white people were in the
United States. You got the vote given to
African American men, and you
got the 14th Amendment. So it's,
that's kind of amazing. And
those don't go away. They're
still there on the books to be
interpreted correctly down the line
somewhere, even though Jim
Crow is a long and ugly
episode of what comes. I mean the
Confederates just, they weren't
confused about being defeated.
They were crushed, and
so they vastly scaled back what
they wanted. They had wanted a
slave-holding republic. They
scaled back for just having white
supremacy and the North, and
that's what happened. You
ended up with white supremacy
and Jim Crow intact--
... which is a lot different
than keeping slavery intact.
- And that set off the whole process of the
Civil Rights Movement that lasted decades.
- I mean, Jim Crow is the clearest
expression of the White South's
reaction to defeat at
Appomattox. "Okay, what can
we get out of this? We
can't get what we wanted.
This is the next best thing, and that's
what we'll get. We'll get Jim Crow."
- You know, when you walk the ground of
some of these battles, Gettysburg,
is there something you can only
experience when you're there?
- In my experience, you cannot replicate
in a classroom what you can do at a
historic site, I mean a
really historic site.
You can... You get people to a
place like that, I've given untold
tours on battlefields and
other historic places.
You can talk about so much more than just
what you can s- First of all, you can
you can understand what happened on the battlefield
better than reading about it or looking at
maps 'cause the terrain
makes it much clearer.
But you can also talk about, okay, what
are the men like in the armies who
are here? Why are they in the ser- A lot of the
things we've talked about today, what's the
status of the war now? What are the
political situations behind the lines? What
difference will this battle
make? What will happen if the
Federals prevail or if the
Confederates prevail? Or you can
use, at a place like Gettysburg,
the memorial landscape as a
wonderful way to talk about memory from
the war. Look at the inscriptions on the
monuments. What was important when they put
these up? And the later monuments, it's ...
The opportunities for a teacher on one of
these sites are just almost unlimited.
- And I don't want to be too woo-woo,
but I also believe from some of the
experience I've had that the land has a
kind of memory. I don't know what it is.
- They have a speech in the
cemetery at Gettysburg on the
anniversary of Lincoln's Gettysburg
Address every year, and I was asked to do
that a few years ago, and it
was just... It was amazing
to me. I mean, there have been
very few things in my career
that are like that, and we
want... We talked, we stopped in
different parts of the cem- There were a
thousand people there. It was an extremely
cold, windy November 19th, and it was
just... Talk about feeling the ghosts
of the past. It was really something
that I've only felt a few times
in my life. It was really
interesting, really interesting.
- You've mentioned the Lost Cause a few
times. What was the Lost Cause? Who
created it, and what did it claim?
- The Lost Cause is the
Confederate memory stream of
the war, and let me just say very, very
briefly, I think there are four main
ways the generation that experienced
the war remembered it. The one
remembered by the most people would be
the majority of white Northerners is what
I call the Union Cause and that the greatest
outcome of the war was putting the nation back
together. It's also good that slavery
was killed. That's important, but
the most important thing was putting the
nation back together. The Emancipation
Cause memory of the war is, yes, it's a good
thing that the Union was saved, but the
most important thing is you killed
slavery. You got rid of this monstrous
institution that had mocked
that language in the founding
documents. So those are both the
winners' versions of the war.
The Confederate version, the Confederates are
in a tough spot. How do we make something
palatable out of this catastrophic
decision we made in 1861?
We'll do this to save slavery, and four years
later, slavery's dead, and a third of all
our white military-age boys are
dead. So here's what we're gonna do.
First of all, it wasn't about slavery. Let's
pretend it wasn't about slavery. It was about high
constitutional principles.
It was about states' rights-
- States' rights
- ... as opposed to central
authority oppressing people.
- Right, right, right.
- And second, we never could have
won. It was a hopeless fight
against long odds, and so
it was a gallant effort in,
in pursuit of constitutional
rights. Okay, that gets us off the
hook there. And who are we gonna look to?
Should we talk about Jefferson Davis?
No, we didn't even like him during the war. I know
who we'll talk about. Let's talk about Robert E.
Lee. He won victories against
the odds. So these are kind
of the main tenets of the Lost Cause. It
wasn't about slavery. We never could have
won. There's no loss of honor in losing a
battle you never could have won, but that
you waged for high constitutional principle.
And let's talk about Lee 'cause we don't
wanna talk about Jefferson Davis, and there's
almost no one else to talk about except maybe
Stonewall Jackson. Those will be our
two boys that we talk about the most.
And that is basically
The short form of the Lost Cause. The fourth
way that people remembered, and this came
a little bit later, was the
reconciliation cause where you...
This is kind of white Northerners and white
Southerners agreeing not to talk about slavery.
Don't talk about emancipation. Let's
talk about shared American virtues of
courage and so forth.
- So some of that still persists
with us today. We look at the
Confederate flag. So some historians argue
for the long, quote, "long Civil War."
- Sure, and it's really long. It's the
Civil War that never ends kind of,
and I certainly think that there
are ramifications from the Civil
War that have never ended. But I think the Civil
War ended, and I think it ended in the early
summer of 1865 with the destruction
of the Confederate government,
the absolute dissolution of all
the Confederate military forces.
I think that is the end of the Civil War.
People at the time thought it was, too. What
comes afterward, the long coda,
Reconstruction is a 12-year
coda to a four-year war that works
out some of the difficulties of
how you put the nation back together.
And then beyond that, you have these
different memory streams that have
been contending with one another
that still... Some of which still
reverberate today, and including
what are you gonna do with the
Confederate flag, which most of... There are
a lot of nitwits around. They don't even
know what the Confederate
flag was. They fly a
rectangular version of
the St. Andrew's cross.
That is not the Confederate flag.
They call it the Confederate flag.
The Confederate flag that had a St.
Andrew's cross wasn't a rectangle, it was a
square, and the actual
Confederate flag had three big
bars and then stars up in... It looks
kind of like the United States flag.
They don't even know that, and they go
around flying it everywhere. It's a
symbol and pretend that it
represents all kinds of things. The
Confederate flag cannot be divorced
from all the times, that version of it,
the St. Andrew's cross version.
Every Ku Klux Klan group flew it.
Every... It's... You just
can't sanitize it. And
I mean, I saw Confederate flags in Britain
and Ireland. I mean, it's become a sort of
up yours symbol I think in some places-
... of just sort of rebellion, not
necessarily- ... tethered specifically-
- Rebellion against inst- institutions
- ... against authority and institutions-
... and the ruling class and the... But
that's... But here it has a very specific
meaning, and you just can't separate
it. It's... People should quit trying.
- So you taught at UVA and lived
through Charlottesville in 2017.
Can you tell me what Charlottesville
was? What did it mean?
- It's really interesting because the
day just before that, I did a long
interview with Katie Couric,
who was working on a s-
on a documentary about
Confederate monuments.
And she and I spent two hours
talking, walking around the
UVA campus, talking about the Confederate
monuments were there. She was a
student at UVA.
She said, "I didn't even know these were here." I
said, "Well, most people don't know they're here.
They're not aware of this, of this
part of the landscape." We had
no idea. Her film crew went out
the next day and filmed what was
going on when they actually
had the violence and the
crowd at the Lee statue, which was downtown.
I didn't go down to watch any of that.
- What's your view on Confederate monuments?
You know, the monuments that capture
these periods, these complicated
periods of our history.
- Well, I have complicated views,
but my main vi- But my, my
first reaction to that is they're not all the
same. They've all... They're treated as if they're
all exactly the same, and
they're not. There's some...
There are the Silent Sam
mo- which was on the
campus at UNC for years. It
had... Some of the rhetoric
when they dedicated that is
really horrific. It's horrible
rhetoric, and I can understand why that needed to
go. There's the... what was called the Battle of
Liberty Place monument in New
Orleans that was a white supremacist
monument very definitely that.
I think that local places should
decide these. Wherever the
monument is, I think that's who should decide,
if the local... And I think there should be a
process how they decide
it. Let people have a
public hearing. But they did that in
Charlottesville actually, had a public hearing.
I went and talked at it. Lots of other
scholars and local people talked at it,
and then they had a commission that
they had set up, and the commission
voted to keep the monuments in place
but re-examine them with text that put
them in context and then put
up monuments, new monuments to
previously ignored groups.
The city council then came in and overrode
that and decided they took them all down
in Charlottesville. They also took down the
Lewis & Clark monument, and there's a Geo-
They took down all the monuments
that had been put up. I think
many of the Confederate monuments, the kind
of ones on courthouse lawns and so forth
that were put up by the Confederate
generation, that is the veterans
themselves and the women who were
alive during the war, tend to be
monuments to the common soldiers,
that just kind of lost generation
of young men. The later
wave of monuments that came
are... were put up by other groups that were
not... They're not really Confederate monuments.
They're put up by... The ones that were put up
in the '20s and '30s. A third wave were put
up in reaction to the civil rights
activities in the '50s and early
'60s, and then a fourth wave
went up after the movie
Gettysburg and Ken Burns' series. But
they're complicated, and I see them
as historical...
And I understand the arguments on both sides. I
understand people who just say they're hateful.
They bring up hateful remembrances. We should
get rid of all of them, every one of them.
I used them as teaching tools in
Charlottesville for years with groups of
teachers and students. There were
five monuments in Charlottesville,
Two that were put up by
veterans—two that were put up by
groups later, the Lee and Jackson statues
were those, and then there were two
bronze plates on the side of
the rotunda that just listed
UVA graduates who died in Confederate
service. Had about 500 names on them.
Those were all of the Confederate
statues there, and it— I used
them to talk about different
strains of memory and used
recon- They're— The Lee, the main
tenor of the Lee statue when it
went up was this
reconciliationist Lee. He, Lee
wanted the nation back together. Lee at Appomattox,
that kind of stuff. Didn't have anything
to do with Jim Crow or white supremacy, although
all the people who put them up probably would've--
Clearly, we would consider them racist.
They were in favor of white supremacy.
But you don't need statues
in the post-war South
and the Jim Crow South. You have
the police force, state law,
local law, state troopers. That's
what enforces white supremacy,
not statues. The historian in me
likes to use them as part
of the historical record,
interpret them, use them to explain
different parts of U.S. history.
That's how I used them. Having
said all that, I did, I do,
did, and still do believe that it should be a
local issue. If a locality decides they don't want
them up anymore, then don't
have them up anymore.
- I think if we ignore history, we're
gonna be doomed to repeat it. I think
that's... We should never
censor books. We should
read books. We should read
Mein Kampf. We should read,
Books that capture a certain moment
in history, even if it's a hateful
moment in history, even if it's a
destructive moment in history. We need to
understand-
- Or have them read texts written at
the time that have language that we
wouldn't use now. It helps you
understand the ti- It's, it's-
There are a lot of hard edges in
the past. There are a lot of nice
edges too that make you feel good, but there are a
lot of really hard edges in the past, and if you're
gonna be serious about coming to terms
with history, you need to accept
that and deal with them and talk
about them and not just try
to erase them, I think. There are
a lot of books that people won't
read now. I taught a graduate
seminar at one point
on foundational 19th century
texts, and one of the texts
I was gonna— that I assigned in
the class was Huckleberry Finn.
And a lot of the students said they wouldn't
read Huckleberry Finn because they knew it had
language in it that they... And
they didn't wanna see those words.
- Even just reading about slavery,
American and otherwise, is hard.
It's really difficult. But,
like, we're capable of that. We
humans are capable of that.
And this doesn't somehow go
away because we agree for it to
go away. We can always return back
to that, maybe in other forms,
in other ways. We can do evil
things unto each other. And I,
I personally believe all of us are
capable of doing evil things unto each
other. And the dark
reality of that is we too
readily convince ourselves
that we're doing good.
- Yeah, because if you're doing
good, you can do anything-
... and it's justified if it's,
if it's good. If the end is good-
... all bets are off. You can
do anything that you wanna do.
- And reading history to realize that,
uh, we need to think deeper and more
critically about our actions and,
and also that history is complicated,
and there's a bunch of different forces,
Is really important. And
also to realize that
individuals can, can turn the
tides of history, can like,
can lead to progress, can
stop evil doing when it's
happening. All of those things. Like,
the power of the individual is immense.
- Yes. I mean, coming back to the
monuments for a minute, it, it's also
worth talking about that even at the time
there were people who... A lot of Union
veterans were against putting up Confederate
monuments. Frederick Douglass had
a problem with the Emancipation
Monument that was in Emancipation Park
on Capitol Hill and talked about the reasons
why he had a pro- "Why is this the image
that you chose for that monument?"
Union veterans, they had a
hard time with Confederate monuments, and
I just think that it is... Almost
everything can be a teaching tool,
un- but it bothers me that certain books
would be proscribed because they have some
language that might bother somebody.
And, and, and it... You need to...
I mean, the language
should bother you. So-
- I think, I think history
truly should bother you.
It, it, the, it should be difficult.
It should be a painful process
to study human history
because if it's not painful,
you're not really understanding
the full range of what we're
capable of. But anyway,
you know, people in the modern day,
I have to ask you about this, kinda
casually talk about the
new Civil War in America.
As somebody who studied the Civil
War, do you think our country
today is divided to a
degree that's on the verge
of something like the Civil
War of the 19th century?
- No, I really don't. And I'm not pr-
And I don't mean to play down the
degree to which... that we are divided.
We are divided. We, we do resemble the
1850s now in that I think
the first impulse on
the part of people on either side
of the political spectrum is to
attribute the worst to the
other side and to, and to not
acknowledge any, any good on the
other side, to attribute the worst
possible characteristics
to the other side,
and to have inflammatory
rhetoric coming from
various directions that, that
really seeks to sort of stir
up as much unhappiness and controversy
as possible. I think we're like the
1850s in that way. But I-- But in terms of
whether we're really at the point
where the kind of actions that I've
dealt with in my study of the Civil War
I, I don't think we're anywhere near
that. And I mean, I really don't. If
we get there, that will be heartbreaking,
but I just don't, I just don't see it.
I don't see physical assaults
against members of Congress on the
floor of the Congress. I don't see...
It's, States talk about seceding if things
don't go... Texas talked about seceding
when Obama was elected. California
talked about seceding when Trump was elected.
But you know what? Neither one of them called a
secession convention and had
delegates go to it. When Lincoln was
elected, they called conventions, they
voted to secede, and they left the
they left the nation. So that's
different to me than talking
about it and threatening it and
posing different scenarios.
- Are there genuine structural
parallels between that time and now,
if you can linger on that?
- Well, I mean, the states
structurally, a state can call a
convention if it wants to,
and to talk about whatever it
wants to talk about. So I suppose
that structure is still in place,
but I haven't seen any serious movement
toward doing something like that.
- Yeah. And I think there's a real
cohesion and resilience to the Union,
as we've talked about. I think people are,
despite the discourse and the
bickering, there's a real
love of nation that maybe is not
often expressed- ... explicitly. But
there is a sense that we're
all in this kinda together,
and that we're yelling at each other. Kinda
like you have a family Thanksgiving dinner
where there's very passionate
yelling and arguing, but there's a kinda
assumption that we're still a family.
At least that's the hope.
You know, one of the questions that the
Civil War asked is, What is America?
So I have to ask you from over 50 years of
studying the Civil War- ... like what,
what do you think? What is this country?
What is this union? What is the
core that makes us who we are?
- Well, I think in a lot of ways
it's much of what it was in the
mid-19th century. I still think it's
a magnet for... I mean, we're in an--
we're far more diverse now as a people
than we were during the Civil War
because we continue to
act in the same way as
it did in the Civil War, only they're not
Germans and people come from everywhere here
now. I mean, they literally
come from everywhere here now.
And everybody doesn't find a nice
easy road here by any means,
and there are lots of things wrong
with the United States. But I still
think the United States acts... Has a
role in the world that's unlike, I
won't say any other place, but I can't
think of a place that's quite like it, that
has so many people coming from so many places,
who somehow manage to fit into
this mosaic. And then I think
most people do have a way to fit into
the mosaic, and then they become part of
the old mosaic when the next
group of people who are not like
them come in, and those are the ones
who are the new ones fitting in.
- Yeah, sometimes I think about,
I'm sorry to romanticize it,
but because I do think that Barack Obama
was one of the great speech makers
of my lifetime. And I sometimes imagine
what Lincoln would have thought
if he could attend an Obama speech.
If he saw that Obama became
president, that an African American
became President of the United States of
America. It's, it seems like
such a trivial thing to say,
But I think it's not trivial at
all. It's one of the great
accomplishments of our country.
- I think one of Lincoln's great attributes
was his humanity comes through
so many things that he wrote.
His real appreciation for
people who faced long odds,
worked against the odds, didn't
begin with advantages in
their favor, and so forth.
I think he and his ability to grow, I
think he would have handled that actually
pretty well. Much better than
many other people I can think of
from the mid-19th century. I think
he had genuine humanity. I think,
I don't think you can read all the
things he wrote and not come to
that conclusion. He also... But,
so does, does he check all our
boxes now? Of course he doesn't. Was he
prejudiced by our standards in some ways?
Of course he was. But I think that he,
I think he would have handled that
pretty well, and he would have been,
still been really tall. Even in our time-
... he'd be way taller than most people.
- Yeah. What you know, 250th birthday,
What gives you hope about
the future of America?
- What gives me hope? I'm, and I'm,
and I'm a grouchy, not optimistic
person in a lot of ways.
- Are you?
- Yeah, I am. I am.
- You had some moments of optimism today.
- I was just gonna say, but for, I do have
moments of optimism, and one of them
I have is in the resiliency of this republic.
I really do have... And it's genuine
optimism. I'm not just... And I know a lot of
people will think that it's naive, but I really...
Because I'm, see what it's been
through, and it's emerged-
... and it's gone forward. And the
trajectory, and this is something O-
that Obama has commented on, and as have
many others, the trajectory is in the
right direction.
With lots of things you wish were different,
but the overall trajectory is in the right
direction. I really do
believe that, and that's why
I tend to be, in that regard, optimistic.
- I think there's a few folks
on the interwebs that talk about
the decline of the American empire,
even using the word
empire. I'm one of the f-
One of the folks who thinks that
America's flourishing. It's, it
is a beacon of hope and
freedom in the world,
and there's a lot to
criticize, the militarism,
And a lot of different aspects
that are hypocritical,
and is not always living up
to the great ideals that it
supposedly represents, but at
least is striving towards that.
And it is still a home
for the great diversity
of humans, as you've mentioned.
That, I think, is one of the great,
beautiful aspects about this country.
And the full mess of it, the drama,
the arguments, the heated passion, the
chaos, the thing that feels
like chaos but I think
ultimately will lead to progress.
I love all of it. I think it
is the greatest nation
on Earth. So on this
250th birthday, I hope
there's 250 years more, and
I'm truly grateful that
there's somebody like you
studying our great history, and I'm grateful
for this wonderful conversation today.
- I appreciate the
invitation. It's been fun.
- Thank you, Gary.
Thank you for listening to this conversation
with Gary Gallagher. To support this
podcast, please check out our sponsors
in the description, where you can
also find links to contact me, ask
questions, give feedback, and so
on. And now, let me leave you with
some words from William Tecumseh
Sherman, a United States
Army general in the Union
Army during the Civil War.
"I am tired and sick of war.
Its glory is all moonshine.
It is only those who have
neither fired a shot nor heard the
shrieks and groans of the wounded
who cry aloud for blood, for
vengeance, for desolation.
War is hell." Thank you for listening,
and hope to see you next time.